<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short view of the fravds, and abvses committed by apothecaries, as well in relation to patients, as physicians, and of the only remedy thereof by physicians making their own medicines by Christopher Merret ...</title>
            <author>Merret, Christopher, 1614-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50701</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R650</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12770109</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12770109</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93631</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50701)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93631)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 699:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short view of the fravds, and abvses committed by apothecaries, as well in relation to patients, as physicians, and of the only remedy thereof by physicians making their own medicines by Christopher Merret ...</title>
                  <author>Merret, Christopher, 1614-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition more correct.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[3], 5-78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Allestry ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 78.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pharmacists --  England.</term>
               <term>Pharmacy --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:93631:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Novemb. 13. 1669.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>SAM. PARKER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93631:1"/>
            <p>A SHORT VIEW OF THE <hi>FRA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DS,</hi> and <hi>AB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SES</hi> Committed by APOTHECARIES; As well in Relation to <hi>PATIENTS,</hi> as
<hi>PHYSICIANS:</hi> AND Of the only Remedy thereof by <hi>PHYSICIANS</hi> making their own MEDICINES.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>CHRISTOPHER MERRETT Dr.</hi> in <hi>Phyſic,</hi> Fellow of the College of <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and of the <hi>Royal Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Fingunt ſe Medicos omnes, Idiota, Sacerdos,</l>
               <l>Nutrix, &amp; Tonſor, <hi>Pharmacopaeus,</hi> Anus.</l> 
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">The Second Edition more correct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Alleſtry,</hi> Printer to the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St.
<hi>Paul's Church-Yard,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93631:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93631:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>Short View</hi> of the <hi>Frauds</hi> and
<hi>Abuſes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> as well in Relation to
<hi>Patients,</hi> as <hi>Phyſicians;</hi> and of the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy thereof by
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> making their own Medicines.</head>
            <p>DOubtleſs it will ſeem ſtrange to moſt men, that after 30 years not unſucceſsful pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in this great City, I ſhould now at laſt forbear ſending my Bills to the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries,</hi> knowing that hereby a whole Company of men intereſſed in the World (who by their number, noiſe, and tricks, may be able to decry any <hi>Phyſician</hi>) will become my implacable adverſaries, and by their private whiſpers of untrue tales, will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to their utmoſt, either to keep me from any new, or ſhuffle me out of my fixt imployment. But not fearing the utmoſt their malice can invent, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim; I ſhall publickly aſſert what I privately pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, preferring the publick good, and the honour of my profeſſion before my own private profit. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I have had ſome experience what their groundleſs anger can do, when they ſome years ſince proclaimed me in their publick Hall their Enemy, for <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93631:3"/> acting the
<hi>College</hi> Intereſt, and of late for ſaving my Patients lives and purſes, by diſpencing <hi>gratis</hi> my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines. Yet I hope no indifferent perſon, when he knows that I have thus long ſlighted their weak endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, will believe I can now at length have ſo poor an end as revenge; eſpecially when they ſhall conſider on the one hand, the univerſal and daily complaints of both <hi>Patient</hi> and <hi>Phyſician,</hi> the great cauſe they have to do ſo, and the little hope of a remedy, and on the other, beſides that general obligation all men have of doing their Country-men good, and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular neceſſity I have of juſtifying my actions, by leaving the World their judg upon the account I ſhall here deliver of them. And laſtly, that which will leave my Enemies not any objection, I take upon me not only a great trouble, but charge, without any other deſign then doing mankind good, by endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to reſtore my profeſſion to its ancient and deſerved honours. And had I none of theſe inducements, I am ſure the vulgar excuſe of friends importunities may be ſatisfactory to all perſons for my publiſhing what I here do, when I muſt acknowledge that many of my Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legues and other Practiſers in ſeveral parts, upon read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe papers furniſhed me not only with ſome bad practices of their own experience, but thereupon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned the publiſhing of them. So that in theſe papers I do but ſpeak the common language of all <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and of very many <hi>Patients.</hi> Neither are all their frauds and abuſes here inſerted, the reſt (perhaps more in number) being reſerved to another opportunity. I ſhall only add by way of preface; that the laſt year a Book was printed on the ſame argument, by an inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93631:3"/> perſon, now <hi>Dr.</hi> in
<hi>Phyſic,</hi> which might have ſpared me this labour, but that it was too large for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones reading, and in ſome things ſhort. It was his fate to be called by them <hi>Fool, Aſs,</hi> and <hi>Simple Fellow,</hi> and much worſe language, bragging that ſome of their <hi>Boys</hi> ſhould anſwer him. But upon more ſerious thoughts, the whole Company have ſuffered it to find the credit it well deſerves, without the leaſt reply but that of revilings.</p>
            <p>In theſe enſuing papers, I hope to prove, that theſe abuſes complain'd of by all ſorts of perſons, ariſe from this only cauſe, that <hi>Phyſicians</hi> diſpence not themſelves ſuch Medicines, they uſe for the relief of their <hi>Patients,</hi> but commit this work to the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> or rather their Servants.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> abuſes generally relate either to the <hi>Medicines, Patients,</hi> or <hi>Phyſicians;</hi> which three do comprehend all I ſhall ſay on this ſubject.</p>
            <p>But the Reader is to take notice, that all here charged on the
<hi>Apothecaries,</hi> is not meant of every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle one, but of ſome, or more of them, and may in a ſhort time in all probability be verified of them all, according as their number, cajoling the ignorant, and bold daring in
<hi>Phyſic</hi> increaſe.</p>
            <p>But before I deſcend to particulars, I ſhall firſt lay down this <hi>Propoſition,</hi> their own confeſſion, and in their own Language, viz. <hi>That they may be the verieſt Knaves in England.</hi> Becauſe they may put in bad ingredients, and more or leſs then the compoſition requires, they may ſubſtitute one thing for another; and all this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being detected, and conſequently not be puniſhed for ſuch miſdemeanors; but more eſpecially in Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93631:4"/> for private mens uſes, wherein they may do what they pleaſe without the leaſt diſcovery of the <hi>Patient,</hi> and from this general confeſſion of theirs, it clearly follows, that whatſoever deceit, covetous wits can invent, may at leaſt be ſuſpected to be uſed by them, and whatſoever is here alledged may find eaſier belief.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Secondly,</hi> Moſt men wonder, that this
<hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration,</hi> being but of few years ſtanding, and to the ſetting up of whoſe Trade ſo ſmall a Stock is neceſſary; ſhould live ſo high, ſpend ſo freely, gain ſo great Eſtates, by their return of ſo little money yearly, which how 'tis done every man may conceive to be effected by the following Artifices.</p>
            <p>More particularly, the Frauds by them committed relate either to their falſifying of <hi>Medicines,</hi> or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to the number of their Bills, and preſcriptions, or thirdly, to the prices of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They uſe <hi>Medicines</hi> quite contrary to the preſcription, <hi>Myrtle-leafs</hi> ſhewed the <hi>Cenſors</hi> for
<hi>Sena,</hi> a Binder for a Purger. <hi>Muſhroms</hi> of the Oak,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> rub'd over with Chalk for <hi>Agaric,</hi> which Mr.
<hi>Evelyn</hi> in his late publiſht Book of <hi>Foreſt Trees,</hi> pag.
27. obſerves, to the great ſcandal of <hi>Phyſic</hi> as he adds;
<hi>Hemlock-Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort</hi> Roots for <hi>Paeony</hi> Roots, Poyſons for wholſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies; <hi>Privet</hi> by ſome, by others
<hi>Dog-berries,</hi> for thoſe of <hi>Spina Cervina,</hi> no Purgers for a ſtrong one. <hi>Sheeps Lungs</hi> for <hi>Fox Lungs,</hi> the <hi>Bone</hi> of an <hi>Oxe Heart</hi> for that of a <hi>Stags Heart, Damſons</hi> for
<hi>Damaſc Prunes,</hi> Syrup of <hi>Limons,</hi> for that of <hi>Citrons, Bryony</hi> Roots for <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choacan,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They falſify the grand Compoſitions of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93631:4"/> the <hi>London Diſpenſatory.</hi> It being a common trade with them to buy unſound, and decayed Simples of ſome
<hi>Druggiſts,</hi> and to return them back ſo much of the compoſition as will pay for the Simples. Secondly, whereas <hi>Apothecaries</hi> are bound to ſhew publickly to the <hi>Cenſors</hi> of the <hi>College,</hi> and the
<hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Wardens</hi> of their Company, <hi>Mithridate, Diaſcordium, Alkermes,</hi> &amp;c. Yet for all this ſome of them privately make a great deal more of the Compoſition then is ſhewed, of unſound Drugs, and ſome without any view at all; others put in the Scrapings that ought to be thrown away; and by theſe Arts they under-ſell, and ruine one another, ſelling the Compoſition at a lower rate then good Ingredients coſt them; and with theſe complaints they daily mutiny amongſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 'Tis very common for them to load Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines with Honey, and other cheaper ingredients, and to leave out in whole or in part, thoſe of greater value; <hi>viz. Saffron</hi> in <hi>Ruffus</hi> Pills, and in <hi>Oxycroceum</hi> Plaſter, which latter, they colour of a
<hi>Saffron</hi> colour with <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meric, Sanders,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>Ambergriſe</hi> in <hi>Alkermes, Diaſcordium</hi> was found by the
<hi>Cenſors</hi> in their ſearch made only of <hi>Honey,</hi> and
<hi>Bole-Armeniac.</hi> Which falſe compoſition was taken away by the then Maſter of the Company.</p>
            <p>Such <hi>Chymiſts</hi> which ſell preparations honeſtly made complain, that few <hi>Apothecaries</hi> will go to the prices of them. Whence it comes to paſs, that moſt of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations found in the Shops are ſophiſticated, to the great abuſe of City and Country. Theſe abuſes daily increaſe ſince the <hi>Cenſors,</hi> diſcouraged by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of <hi>Empirics</hi> ſwarming in every Corner, have omitted their wonted ſearches, being to their loſs of <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93631:5"/> and expences out of their own Purſes for the publick good only. Now ſince the
<hi>Chymical</hi> Oyls, by reaſon of their great prices are moſt of them adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, and very few of them right good, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hath been publiſhed on this matter, and to leave the buyers of them unexcuſable, I ſhall here add briefly, yet ſufficiently the ways to diſcover theſe Cheats. Firſt for ſweet-ſcented <hi>Chymical</hi> Oyls, <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe of <hi>Cloves, Cinnamon,</hi> and <hi>Saſſaphras.</hi> Only drop a little of them into fair water, and that part which is true good will ſink under the water, but the adultera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted part will ſwim on the top of it. Some others draw deep tinctures from the ſaid Spices with Spirit of Wine highly rectified, and ſell them for the Oyls; but theſe mix with the water throughout, neither ſwimming, nor ſinking. Others more craftily digeſt with the ſaid tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures ſome of the true Oyls, which compound being put into water, will for a time render it white. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way of ſophiſticating is with Oyl of <hi>Turpentine</hi> mixed in great quantity with that which is adultera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; You may eaſily diſcover the Oyl of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> by ſetting it on fire, for it yields abundance of ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcented ſmoak, with very little ſavour of the Herb, Flour, or Seed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſoon takes fire. To correct the ill ſmell of the <hi>Turpentine,</hi> they digeſt it with, and diſtilit off with <hi>Spirit of Wine.</hi> Thoſe ſophiſticated with <hi>Turpentine,</hi> fired in a Silver Spoon colour it, and quickly diffuſe themſelves upon a Knife, or Paper. The beſt way to try by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iring, is to put a drop or two of theſe Oyls on the end of a broad pointed Knife, which being firſt heated, and then thruſt into a lighted Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, preſently take fire, and break out into a flame <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93631:5"/> with much dark ſmoak; but if you will try them in a Spoon, heat it firſt over a Candle, and then blow the flame of lighted paper, or of a Wax Candle on them. To try the ſcent, blow out the flame of the good Oyls, and your ſmell will ſoon diſcover the ill ſcent of the <hi>Turpentine</hi> from that of the good Oyl. But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, all Oyls drawn from Plants by diſtillation hardly flame, and the flame ſoon goes out, and the ſmoak gives a full flavour of the Plant it ſelf, whereas thoſe ſophiſticated as before, differ from the true in both. The ſame Oyls are alſo ſophiſticated with cheap ones drawn from decayed <hi>Oringes,</hi> and <hi>Limons;</hi> Your ſmell on firing will ſoon diſcover theſe mixtures. A third way of ſophiſticating
<hi>Chymical</hi> Oyls is, by mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them ſuch Oyls as are made by expreſſion, which are eaſily diſcovered by rubbing them on white paper, which being held and dryed at the fire, the <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical</hi> part ſoon flyes away, and leaves the paper tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparent, looking no otherwiſe then oyled paper; but pure <hi>Chymical</hi> Oyls totally fly away, leaving the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per white as 'twas before, and not tranſparent, and in this way Oyl of ſweet Almonds and Spike have a great ſhare. As for Oyls drawn by
<hi>Retort,</hi> they all of them ſmell ſo ſtrong of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire, that neither ſmell nor taſt can well diſcover any fraud in them. Now for the <hi>fixed Salts,</hi> moſt of them are made of the Aſhes of <hi>Tobacco-ſtalks,</hi> &amp;c. More might be ſaid for the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Cheats of other
<hi>Chymical</hi> preparations, which ſhall be reſerved to another opportunity, and had <hi>Phyſicians</hi> juſt encouragement, they would ſpend both their time and moneys on the like diſcoveries for the publick Utility.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93631:6"/>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Add to the former (though perhaps 'tis an error of ignorance only) that if ſuch Simples are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed they know not, they fetch from the Herb-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men what they give them, true or falſe; for many of theſe Women give to very many Plants falſe names; Now if the <hi>Apothecary</hi> be ſo careful to conſult an Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal, which few have, and fewer know how to make uſe of, yet they too frequently miſtake the thing by reaſon of ſeveral names given to the ſame thing, or of one name to ſeveral things, and many of them conſult the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Dictionaries</hi> only, which are moſt erroneous in the names of natural things; inſomuch that in my firſt practice (being curious of theſe particulars) I have found two or three miſtakes in one preſcription, a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of which miſtakes, and names ill given, I had collected, but the late fire conſumed it, though many of them my memory hath reſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Many of the <hi>London,</hi> and moſt of the
<hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-Apothecaries,</hi> buy of the whole-ſale men, who affirm of one another, eſpecially of ſuch who gain great Eſtates in ſhort time, that they cannot ſell their Medicines honeſtly made at ſo low a rate as they do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> I ſhall need to ſay little of ſuch
<hi>diſtilled waters,</hi> as diſcover themſelves neither to ſmell, nor taſt, but ſhall only recite a known Story of an <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary,</hi> who chid his man for ſending away a Cuſtomer that came for <hi>Plantan</hi> water, telling him there was enough at the Pump.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> As for <hi>Ointments,</hi> and
<hi>Plaſters,</hi> they are ſold by ſome at ſo low a price,
<hi>viz.</hi> 3<hi>d. per</hi> l. for <hi>Ointments,</hi> as I have been informed, that 'tis not poſſible to make <pb n="13" facs="tcp:93631:6"/> them at, and yet ſuch however falſifyed maintain a trade amongſt Country, and low-priced City-<hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries,</hi> and the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> profeſs they cannot effect their Cures with the Shop-Medicines, and that this is the reaſon why they make their own <hi>Oyls, Oyntments,</hi> &amp;c. as the
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> Charter allows them to do; and why may not
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> think this to be the cauſe why they ſometimes fail in their Cures, as well as <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons?</hi> and alſo make their own Medicines as well as they, eſpecially ſince the <hi>Apothecary</hi> may as eaſily falſify, and to greater profit in the one, then in the other?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> As to their uſe of bad or decayed
<hi>Drugs,</hi> 'tis ſo common a practice that I ſhall need to give but one notorious inſtance of it, and 'tis this; I having oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to uſe ſome Seeds, ſent for them to a Seedſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the Meſſenger deſiring to have thoſe of the ſame Year. The Tradeſman knowing him to live with me, aſked, if they were for Phyſical uſe, he replyed in the affirmative, whereat he preſently ſhewed him others, which were of 6 or 7 years old (as he confeſſed) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming them to be as good for that uſe as the neweſt, which he ſold only for ſowing, and that he kept the others, though never ſo old, for the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> only, who ſtill aſked for them, buying them though 20 years old, not regarding if they were decayed and wholy effete (for no Seed will preſerve its vegetative faculty above 7 years much leſs its Phyſical) ſo they could but have them cheap. Beſides their pretty knacks (as they call them) of making their Compounds fair to the eye, more vendible, but worſe for uſe, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring them to their colour and conſiſtence, that <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93631:7"/> they may paſs for good, which perhaps 'tis better to paſs over in ſilence, leſt by confuting I ſhould teach the younger Fry, who may better be honeſtly ignorant of them. Now for their ſubſtituting one thing for another, and detracting where they pleaſe, I ſhall add but one Story of an <hi>Apothecary,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his man (who told him they had no good <hi>Rhabarb</hi> in the houſe) that he ſhould put in dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble quantity of what they had. Nay I have known one ſimple of a quite different nature uſed for a whole compoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> I ſhall conclude this ungrateful Diſcourſe, with ſaying that by reaſon more frauds may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> then by any other Trade, and by ſuppoſition that gain will tempt moſt men to diſhoneſt actions, eſpecially where they may act undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; I ſay, that this ſeems to be the cauſe why they have two Superviſors ſet over them more then any Company that I know of,
<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Cenſors</hi> of the <hi>College</hi> of
<hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and the <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Wardens</hi> of their own Company.</p>
            <p>The next thing is the inlarging and multiplying their Bills and Medicines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> When in Chronical Diſeaſes a
<hi>Phyſician</hi> is conſulted, they go on of their own heads with the ſame preſcription, frequently enough to the Patients great diſadvantage, both of health and purſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> By giving and intermixing Medicines of their own Phancy, with the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> preſcriptions, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome pleaſing Medicine, whereby too often the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> intention is quite croſt, and the effect made uncertain, and hazardous.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:93631:7"/>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By giving Medicines themſelves on ſmall accounts, and ſuch as require only a good ordering, and no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> By repeating long courſes of
<hi>Phyſic</hi> unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly, and needleſly, when either nothing, or very little is needful to be done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> By creating diſeaſes in eaſie mens Phanſies, and ſo decoying them into courſes of <hi>Phyſic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Some of them get private and worthleſs receipts, and ſell them at what rate they pleaſe; Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi> by one Pill alone, though not a very ſafe one, got ſome thouſands of pounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> If one of them get a private receipt from a
<hi>Phyſician</hi> called by the inventor his <hi>Noſtrum,</hi> if ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Apothecary</hi> have occaſion to uſe it, he ſhall be ſure to pay ſawce for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Another trick is when the <hi>Patient</hi> is cured, and the <hi>Phyſician</hi> therefore hath given over his Viſits, then comes the <hi>Apothecary</hi> and inſinuates by his words and paſſions, either ſome danger of relapſe, or ſome other preſent diſtemper, and repairs to the <hi>Phyſician</hi> for a Bill to cure the imaginary diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> But their principal Art of all is, to cry up, and bring in to <hi>Patients</hi> ſuch <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> who through deſign muſt comply with the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Intereſt, and ſuch Practiſers they extol and cry up for good <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> which ſome of them call more expreſly good <hi>Apothecaries Phyſicians,</hi> and ſuch without doubt, the whole Company will endeavour to raiſe unto a fame and practice. But ſuch as write only for the good of the
<hi>Patient,</hi> and not at all for the benefit of the <hi>Apothecary</hi> (as all honeſt men ought to do) they will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93631:8"/> to prevent their calling in, or to ſhuffle them out.</p>
            <p>Now this good <hi>Apothecaries Phyſician,</hi> they deſcribe by his frequent though needleſs viſits, but eſpecially by the multitude of his Bills, by his viſiting twice a day, or oftner (a very careful and painful <hi>Doctor</hi>) and by ſtill writing new Medicines, when half the former, or perhaps none of them have been taken, making an
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> Shop in the <hi>Patients</hi> Houſe, planting the Cupboards and Windows with Glaſſes and Gally-Pots, and not a quarter of the whole made uſe of. He preſcribes a Medicine for every ſlight complaint, and never goes away from the <hi>Patient,</hi> or the <hi>Patient</hi> from him, without a Bill, for fear of the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> grumbling.</p>
            <p>And from this burdening the ſick with multiplicity of Medicines, too often contrary to, and deſtructive one of another, it proceeds that in the <hi>Small Pox,</hi> and <hi>Meaſles,</hi> many are afraid to uſe
<hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the care of the ſick to <hi>Nurſes,</hi> and <hi>Old Women,</hi> and perhaps ſometimes not without cauſe, for by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al multiplication of Medicines, the humours of the body may be made, or kept in too great a ſtate of flui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, whence the <hi>Flox</hi> followeth. Whereas a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine or two duly adminiſtred, may ſuffice to bring them well forth, and then there needs no more but good ordering, unleſs perhaps ſome accident ariſe, which may require further care. And here as well as in other Caſes, the <hi>Patient</hi> is to be rectified, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> Viſits, and yet diſmiſſeth him without a reward, unleſs he writes a Bill, whereas it might have been better if nothing at all had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, <pb n="17" facs="tcp:93631:8"/> and the <hi>Phyſician</hi> left to his own judgment; and hence it is that many enlarge their Bills, that the Patient may think he hath enough for his money, whereby the <hi>Apothecary</hi> is gratified, who ought to commend the Medicines as neceſſary for the ſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſingular in themſelves, whereas in truth this great farcy proves ungrateful to the taſt and ſtomach; inconvenient to health, by curing one diſeaſe, but creating more; and by this means keeping them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in a way of <hi>Phyſic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A third</hi> abuſe of the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> relates to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Medicines; firſt they put what rates they pleaſe on their Simples, Compounds, and Receipts, and none are judges of them, but thoſe of their own Trade; inſomuch that they gain a 11<hi>d.</hi> in the Shilling, if they ſay true of themſelves. Whereas the <hi>Colleges of Phyſicians</hi> beyond Sea, yearly ſet a tax upon the <hi>Simples,</hi> and
<hi>Compounds</hi> of the Shops. So that the Cuſtomer can tell the price of what he hath oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to uſe, and not ſtand at the mercy of the
<hi>Apothecary</hi> to rate them as he liſts, and to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they put in print the prices of them every year.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Suppoſe a <hi>Phyſician</hi> hath preſcribed a Pint of <hi>Juleb,</hi> &amp;c. to be taken at four ſeveral times, ſome <hi>Apothecaries</hi> carry not the whole pint at once, but divide it into four parts, and carry but one at a time, and ſo of other Medicines, and then will charge their Bill for every ſingle <hi>Potion,</hi> or Draught, as they ought the whole Pint; ſo that by this Art they gain four times as much for the whole Medicine as in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience they ought; and a
<hi>Juleb,</hi> which coſt them ſix <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93631:9"/> pence, will be rated at 10, 12, or more Shillings. But perhaps 'tis fit they ſhould be paid for their created Viſits; and for this unneceſſary officiouſneſs, perſons of great eſtates may be contented to pay roundly, if they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> When a <hi>Phyſician</hi> hath preſcribed 20 Pills, ſome of the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> will make 30 of them, under pretence the <hi>Patient</hi> cannot ſwallow them elſe; now reckoning each Pill at a certain rate (as they uſually do) they gain a third part more then they ought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To advance the prices, you ſhall hardly ever ſee a Bill without <hi>Bezoar,</hi> or <hi>Pearls</hi> in it, to make people think them very chargeable; whereas ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there is not above a grain or two of theſe dear ingredients in the preſcription, and a few grains of theſe or <hi>Ambergriſe</hi> doubles or trebles the prices of the Medicines, and are ſure never to be omitted in their Bills, beſides the guilding of the Pills, and covering their <hi>Boluſſes,</hi> and
<hi>Electuaries</hi> with <hi>Cold</hi> (which have only an imaginary and no real uſe in Medicines ſo uſed) much inhanſeth their prices, and a rich
<hi>Cordial</hi> inſerted exceedingly advanceth moſt of their Bills; or if China or any other dear ingredient be in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt 'tis not omitted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Some <hi>Apothecaries</hi> offer, and perhaps ſome <hi>Phyſicians</hi> have taken preſents to help them to Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers, which muſt neceſſarily be ſqueazed out of their higher-rated Medicines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> I have heard ſome prudent perſons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of their bringing in their Bills but once in a year, or two; ſuppoſing they made them pay <hi>Lombards</hi> 
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93631:9"/> Uſury for their forbearance. And through this neglect they ſometimes loſe their money, and whether they raiſe other Mens Bills to make up theſe loſſes, I affirm not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Another cauſe of raiſing their prices is a neceſſity of keeping in their Shops ſuch Medicines as are ſeldom uſed, or ſuch as muſt upon neceſſity decay, and grow uſeleſs. Now ſuppoſe they throw ſuch away, this reaſon is good, but you will find a remedy for this hereafter.</p>
            <p>To conclude this ſecond Complaint. By reaſon of the dear Bills of the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> many are deterred from going to the
<hi>Phyſician,</hi> and run to common <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks,</hi> and I think this to be the reaſon (as ſome diſabuſed perſons have confeſſed to me) why they have ſo much cryed up the abilities of <hi>Apothecaries</hi> for pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, becauſe they would ſave their credit in taking <hi>Phyſic</hi> of them. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> candidly in his Book of Confeſſions declares, that through covetouſneſs he repeated a courſe of
<hi>Phyſic,</hi> without conſulting the <hi>Phyſician</hi> (who had before cured him of the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe) to his greater charge, danger of his life, and offence againſt God.</p>
            <p>Having done with the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> abuſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating chiefly to the <hi>Patients</hi> Health and Purſe, and ſuch as are willfully committed (though all of them reflect on the <hi>Phyſician</hi>) I ſhall now touch on a few neglects, and miſtakes proving often very miſchievous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They frequently miſtake the
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, which of what dangerous conſequence it is, every one can tell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:93631:10"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They carry a Medicine appointed for one ſick perſon to another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They often neglect the ſending of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines in due time, eſpecially ſuch as have no Servants, or but raw ones, when the Maſter is out of Town, or upon long viſits.</p>
            <p>Having now done with the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late principally to the ſick, I ſhall in the next place ſpeak of them, as they relate to <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and that either to the profeſſion in general, or to the particular practiſers of it.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in general, they endeavour to extirpate them, and ſome have been ſo bold to ſay, they hope in few years to ſee never a <hi>Phyſician</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and to profeſs they will ſcramble with them for practice. And that this hath been and is their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the following particulars will clearly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They have always endeavoured and aimed at the depreſſion and ruine of the <hi>College</hi> of <hi>Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the only <hi>Corporation</hi> of that Art in <hi>England,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering rightly, that the depreſſion of the <hi>College</hi> is their intereſt and riſe, and that the total ſubverſion of it will make them abſolute Maſters in <hi>Phyſic,</hi> and <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> their Servants. In Order hereunto they have conſtantly, both publickly and privately oppoſed the <hi>College</hi> in whatſoever hath been offered to ſetle the liberty of practice on them, their only priviledg and ſubſiſtence, though they have been offered all they could deſire for the ſecurity of their Trade, and legal employment, and far beyond whatſoever any Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> in all, or in any forreign part <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93631:10"/> enjoy, yet nothing would ever content them, but an unlawful, unreaſonable, dangerous, and deſtructive Uſurpation of liberty to ſome pretended practice, that thereby they might gain the whole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They have continually traduced the
<hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege,</hi> and troubled them in <hi>Parliaments,</hi> at the
<hi>Council</hi>-Board, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to their great charge and moleſtation. And for ſuch their great demerits againſt the
<hi>College,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Council, Anno</hi> 1639. granted a <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> to the <hi>Attorney General</hi> (the
<hi>Judges</hi> having firſt heard the whole matter) to take away their
<hi>Charter,</hi> which doubtleſs had been effected, had not the troubles, and long civil War immediately enſued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And in this preſent <hi>Parliament,</hi> how did they endeavour to prepoſſeſs the Members of the Houſe of Commons with ſtrange, and falſe prejudices and aſſertions drawn from irrational, and groundleſs ſuppoſitions, making us the greateſt Tyrants in the World, inferring ridiculouſly that a <hi>Lady,</hi> or Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<hi>Gentlewoman</hi> (for in that believing Sex they have gain'd a great deal of ground by their falſities) might not give the Poor a <hi>Cordial,</hi> &amp;c. without being que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned by the <hi>College;</hi> whereas they know in their Conſciences, that the <hi>College</hi> hath power enough by their firſt Charter to act as much in this kind againſt themſelves, and all other perſons, as they deſired of this preſent <hi>Parliament;</hi> And yet neither <hi>Apothecary,</hi> or any other who practiſed charitably, were ever trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for ſo doing. They pretended alſo they were abridged wholy from their Trade, and might not ſell a penny-worth of <hi>Mithridate,</hi> &amp;c. without a <hi>Doctors</hi> 
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93631:11"/> Bill. Whereas there's not a word in the Charter to that purpoſe; the ſole intent whereof was to keep them as well as other <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> from preſcribing (which they call ſelling) the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> only lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. And as to the Bill it ſelf ſo much railed on by them in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall, Coffee-Houſes, Ale-Houſes,</hi> &amp;c. 'tis eaſie to make it out, that this Charter as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed gives the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> more liberty and freedom of exerciſing their lawful Trade, then is enjoyed in any other Nation, where both Corporations are erected; and that it doth in nothing infringe, or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh their freedom as <hi>Citizens,</hi> or their Charter as <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries;</hi> and that our Charter was compiled by ſome, and peruſed and approved by others the moſt eminent <hi>Lawyers</hi> in
<hi>England</hi> for Worth and Place; and yet none of theſe could find any thing in it either Illegal, Tyrannical, or unfit to be deſired of the
<hi>Parliament.</hi> Nay many miſ-informed Members being rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the true ſtate of the matter, have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the juſtice of it; And was no more then King <hi>James</hi> by his Letters Patents, dated the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> in the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of his Reign, granted to the ſaid <hi>College;</hi> near about the ſame time the
<hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> Charter was granted; and being almoſt nothing elſe but a ſupply of what was ſhort in their former Grants, <hi>viz.</hi> That whereas their Charter granted by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, gave power to puniſh offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the practice of Phyſic; and becauſe there was no power given to ſummon, nor penalty impoſed for non-appearance of ſuch offenders; therefore by their non-appearance, the ſaid power of the
<hi>Cenſors</hi> was eluded; for no ſuch offenders would appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93631:11"/> them, and conſequently no puniſhment could be inflicted on them, according to the true meaning of the ſaid Act. Now this Charter ſo much declaimed againſt, prayed only a ſupply of this defect, and alſo better and more neceſſary ways and means, without which, ſuch and all other offenders againſt the lives and healths of his Majeſties Subjects could not be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; and they had reaſon not to doubt a grant of the ſaid power, ſince by the ſaid Charter a power was granted them to impriſon offenders, whom the Keepers of the Priſons would not receive, becauſe no command, nor penalty was impoſed on them, for not receiving ſuch offenders ſent by the <hi>Cenſors</hi> (a thing ridiculous to our preſent Lawyers) however this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect was ſupplyed by an Act in the firſt of Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> Now whereas ſince the making of the ſaid Acts and Powers, granted to the <hi>College,</hi> ſeveral other Trades, beſides the
<hi>Apothecaries,</hi> relating to Phyſic (being then all Members of the Grocers Company) <hi>viz.</hi> Druggiſts, Chymiſts, Sellers of Strong-waters and Oyls, have aroſe diſtinct from each others, and many abuſes have been and are committed in each of them, as they all confeſs. The ſaid Charter prays for the publick good only (there being the ſame reaſon of all) they might have the ſame power of Surveying them alſo, as they have of the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> which moſt of the Judicious, and ſober of the ſaid Companies, as well in relation to their own private profit, and alſo the publick, by having all Medicines good, did not oppoſe, but liked well of. Nay there was nothing in the ſaid Charter, but what was judged good by all or moſt of the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> ſeveral times conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <pb n="24" facs="tcp:93631:12"/> by Order of the King and his Council, to deliver their opinions concerning ſome Quaeries, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed the main of what was deſired and petitioned for by the <hi>College,</hi> of this preſent Parliament. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Committee</hi> could make report to the Houſe, the <hi>Parliament</hi> was adjourned, whereupon <hi>Apothecaries</hi> falſly gave out, and made people believe our Charter was taken from us. And in this tranſaction before the <hi>Committee,</hi> one <hi>Cocket</hi> an
<hi>Apothecary</hi> exhibited in the name of the <hi>Chymiſts</hi> ſuch a Scandalous Libel, as the <hi>Committee</hi> would not ſuffer to be read; drawn as ſome conceive by the aſſiſtance, and countenance, if not contrivance of his Company.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Company of the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> are bound by their Charter to bring their Servants (before they make them Free) to be examined by the <hi>Cenſors</hi> of our <hi>College,</hi> and to have their approbation of their fitneſs to exerciſe their Art, and ſet up their Trade. Now that they have herein neglected their duty, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently may be diſ-franchiſed and loſe their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms for this omiſſion, 'tis manifeſt not only by the vapours of ſome of them to ſome members of our Body, that they never underwent this examination; but alſo by comparing of our Regiſter (wherein are recorded the names of all ſuch as have been exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) with theirs, if they keep any for this purpoſe. Sure I am, that in two years together, when I was <hi>Cenſor,</hi> very few, if any, did appear to their examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereas yearly a very great number ſet up their Trades. Nay ſince the firing of <hi>London</hi> not one
<hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> Servant hath been examined by the <hi>Cenſors,</hi> for more then theſe three Years laſt paſt, in which time
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93631:12"/> perhaps no leſs then 100 have been made free by the Company.</p>
            <p>Before our preſenting this Charter to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> they would admit no Arbitrators betwixt our Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and Theirs, not contenting themſelves with their Charter lately granted in <hi>King James's Reign,</hi> and that by the procurement of ſome of our <hi>College</hi> for theſe unthankful perſons. For they would not refer themſelves (as the
<hi>Chirurgeons</hi> without many words or diſpute did) to the moſt upright, and moſt knowing Sir <hi>Orlando Bridgeman</hi> then <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice,</hi> and now <hi>Lord Keeper,</hi> for a clauſe to be by him drawn, in order to preſerve their immunities and Charter; which they refuſed, fearing belike he would exclude them from the Practice of
<hi>Phyſic,</hi> which the Law hath already done, and which is all they could doubt of; but the Corporation of <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> did acquieſce in the clauſe drawn by the ſaid <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice,</hi> and never appeared before the Committee againſt the ſaid Charter.</p>
            <p>Their increaſing diſ-reſpect, and undervaluing the
<hi>College,</hi> appears in this, that of late years they place our
<hi>Cenſors</hi> invited to their new Maſters Dinner, at their ſecond Table; whereas always heretofore they were ſeated at the firſt Table, next to the Maſter of the Company.</p>
            <p>And to hinder the building of a New <hi>College,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Contribution of the Honorary Fellows thereunt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they tell them that we deceived them in their adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, and never intend the building of a New <hi>College<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> though a large contribution hath been made, and <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93631:13"/> ground purchaſed in order thereunto by the Members of their Corporation.</p>
            <p>And their further deſign appears in their great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing, and rejoycing when any illiterate perſon hath gained any reputation for a Cure performed, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally where <hi>Phyſicians</hi> have been concerned, though the <hi>Patients</hi> neglect or obſtinateneſs, have been the ſole cauſe of this non-performance, and by their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed detraction from
<hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and applauding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, hoping by the former, that people will think ſuch <hi>Mountebanks</hi> able to do better Cures then learned <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and then they can eaſily inſinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſuperior to ſuch <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> and conſequently to
<hi>Phyſicians.</hi> By the latter, they ſeek to depreſs, and level us to themſelves, being conſcious they can never riſe to that worth and ability, required in a <hi>Phyſician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another manifeſt ſign of their endeavour to uſurp our Practice is, their abſurd calling the ſick their <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents,</hi> for
'tis moſt certain that in all reaſon and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage the <hi>Phyſician</hi> and <hi>Patient</hi> only have relation to each other, but not to the
<hi>Apothecary,</hi> who is but a Tradeſman, and manual Operator. Now a Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and his Cuſtomer, or Chapman, are Relatives each to other, but thoſe <hi>Apothecaries</hi> who intrude themſelves and uſurp on our profeſſion, may call their Cuſtomers <hi>Patients,</hi> and that in a true literal ſence, when by their ignorance they make them really ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers under them; and if they deny <hi>Apothecary</hi> and
<hi>Patient</hi> to be non-ſence, they ſhew themſelves pitifully ignorant in the Laws, and Rules of Reaſon, or elſe <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93631:13"/> profeſs themſelves <hi>Phyſicians.</hi> And the like non-ſence they commonly utter by calling <hi>Phyſicians</hi> that make their own Medicines,
<hi>Mountebanks</hi> and <hi>Quacks,</hi> whereas none can be ſuch but thoſe who practiſe without Lawful Authority, as the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> &amp;c. do; and they are not ignorant in this their malice, that the Law of
<hi>England</hi> would puniſh them roundly for ſo ſaying; And were I troubleſome or vindicative, I could make ſome of them examples, but I freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their ſlanders in this kind that are paſt.</p>
            <p>Having done with the main part of the Diſeaſe, next follows the Remedy; and the only firm and proper one will appear to be, that
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> make their own Medicines; the benefit whereof to the publick, the reaſonableneſs of the thing it ſelf, the neceſſity in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> will be manifeſt by that which follows.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi> All that hath been ſaid demonſtrates this laſt propoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The deſire of moſt perſons, and the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all wiſe men, who ſay we are wanting to our own intereſt, if we make not uſe of the remedy in our own hands, performing our Art in all its members, whereof making of Medicines is a chief one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The common practice, and conſtant uſage of all former and antient <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in all other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in
<hi>England</hi> alſo (for 'tis eaſie to ſay when there was not one
<hi>Apothecary</hi> in this Kingdom) the Laws of our Nation, nay even the
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> Charter allow it, the Language of all
<hi>Phyſicians,</hi> our <hi>College</hi> voting it honourable ſo to do, nay <hi>Apothecaries</hi> themſelves com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93631:14"/> it in ſuch <hi>Phyſicians</hi> as buy their Medicines of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Kings <hi>Phyſicians</hi> have formerly made the Kings Medicines, as 'tis manifeſt by my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> in his
4<hi>th.</hi> Book of the Inſtitutes, <hi>part</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 251. where he comments on <hi>Rot. Pat.</hi> 32 <hi>H.</hi> 6. m. 17. He there firſt recites the Roll it ſelf, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are appointed (the King being then ſick) 3 <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> and 2 <hi>Chirurgeors,</hi> to freely miniſter and execute Phyſic about the Kings Perſon, and there are alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited in general, Medicines external, and internal. And on this Roll
<hi>Coke</hi> among other things infers, that the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> may uſe the aid of thoſe <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> named in the Warrant, but of no
<hi>Apothecary,</hi> but to prepare and do all things themſelves,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the reaſon of all this is, the precious regard had of the health and ſafety of the King, who is the head of the Common-wealth. And I am told by one of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſties <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> that the King himſelf affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heretofore we are unwiſe in neglecting our duty herein, and lately of theſe papers, that 'twas the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick intereſt ſo to do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly, Chirurgeons</hi> (as before) will not truſt them to make external Remedies; and the King, and <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company commit the making of their Cheſts for their Fleets to the <hi>Chirurgeons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Have not Ladies and Charitable Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women their Cloſets well furniſhed with various Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines for the Poors uſe, and for their own alſo, when <hi>Phyſicians</hi> are called to their houſes in the Country? Diſtillers of Strong-waters, Makers of Plaiſters, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectioners make Medicines bought by the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:93631:14"/> Ale-Houſes ſell purging Drinks, and Book-ſellers ſell Chymical Medicines, and all this without much regret of the
<hi>Apothecaries.</hi> But if a <hi>Phyſician</hi> intermix a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine with theirs, though the <hi>Patients</hi> life be ſaved thereby, what noiſe, and murmuring, and proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it the next Market-day to the reſt of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany? to what purpoſe any one may judg.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Why ſhould not <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> being law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully authorized thereunto, practiſe with their own Medicines, as well as the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> with theirs, though againſt Law, and incurring thereby the penalty of 5<hi>l. per</hi> Month, which the <hi>College</hi> never troubled them for, or exacted of them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly, Phyſicians</hi> will be neceſſitated to it for their ſubſiſtence and honour, and to preſerve their Art from being proſtituted to illiterate perſons, the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> becoming now their Competitors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> By this means <hi>Phyſicians</hi> will avoid multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of inconveniencies, proceeding from writing of Bills, and the
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> Viſits.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The miſtakes, and frauds in the Ingredients, eſpecially committed by the great practiſing <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> who may, as appears by the following ſtory, be ſuſpected to ſend, inſtead of what was preſcribed, the remains of his own practice, or elſe ſome caſt-by Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; for elſe how could it be when a Medicine was preſcribed to ſtand in Infuſion or ſteep a whole night, that it ſhould be brought two hours after the Bill was written, even the very ſame Evening? Which by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the <hi>Patient</hi> confeſſed, wanting the expected ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> By this courſe <hi>Phyſicians</hi> will avoid the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny opprobrious terms caſt upon them by
<hi>Apothecaries:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93631:15"/>As <hi>Firſt,</hi> In ſaying that if he had not omitted or added ſomething, the <hi>Patient</hi> might have miſcarried; which he may ſay at pleaſure without any contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though doubtleſs many have been killed by this means.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> By ſaying the Bill could never have been made without ſome alteration of the <hi>Apothecary,</hi> thereby inſinuating the
<hi>Doctors</hi> ignorance in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> In ſaying the <hi>Doctor</hi> is not verſed in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, becauſe forſooth he varieth not at every Viſit, and multiplieth not new Bills for the <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> profit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> In ſaying they teach <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and help them to, and in their practice. The firſt and laſt are vile and fooliſh Scandals; as to the Second, 'tis true indeed, that younger
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> recommend <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> to their acquaintance; but 'tis no longer then they have learned enough (as they think) to ſet up for themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fiſthly,</hi> In ſaying, they knew before-hand what ſuch a <hi>Doctor</hi> would preſcribe, and hence it is they have nick-named ſome <hi>Phyſicians</hi> of no mean practice, by the Medicines they frequently uſe, which names in reſpect to the perſons, I ſhall conceal; and of ſuch <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> they brag they can preſcribe as well as they. But if a <hi>Phyſician</hi> adviſe things unknown to them, or out of the common tract, then they ſay the <hi>Doctor</hi> intends to puzzle them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> He will avoid the cenſure of his Bills, which every pitiful fellow, nay their very Boys will abſolve or condemn at pleaſure, and that openly too, nay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <pb n="31" facs="tcp:93631:15"/> to the
<hi>Patient</hi> himſelf, and thereby call in his good <hi>Apothecaries Phyſician.</hi> Now what a ſhame is it, that a <hi>Phyſicians</hi> credit and livelihood, ſhould ſtand at the mercy of ſuch pitiful ignorant, and ſelf-ended Souls? I have heard one of them ſay of the now moſt Eminent Practiſer in <hi>London,</hi> that his Boy could write as good a Method as he, and that he underſtood the practice of <hi>Phyſic</hi> as well as any
<hi>Phyſician</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> except 2, or 3, though the ſame perſon was ſoon made to confeſs, he neither knew the Diſeaſe, Cauſe, nor Cure of a Pleuriſy, pretended to be throughly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He will avoid the trouble put upon him after he hath writ his Bill, by the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in not underſtanding it, who to be inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed came to the <hi>Doctor</hi> heretofore, with their Hats off, but now ſend their Boys, who ſoon put theirs on. Such reſpect do they give <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> when they come to them as to their Maſters to teach them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He will avoid the impertinent Viſits of the
<hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and non-ſenſical, troubleſome, and diſcouraging, frightful diſcourſes to the <hi>Patient,</hi> of whom no man can expect more then the Common Proverb gives to Praters, and impertinent Speakers,
<hi>That they talk like Apothecaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fiſthly,</hi> He will avoid the miſchiefs from their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits, who by their ſhrugs, ſigns, or words, may diminiſh the
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> reputation, and good opinion, whether in his ſkill, or Medicines, whereby good Medicines are neglected, and the expectation of a good ſucceſs upon the uſe of them taken away, or at leaſt cauſing an
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93631:16"/> averſeneſs to them; which actings do exceedingly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice the <hi>Patient,</hi> in reference to his Cure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> He will avoid this inconvenience, that ſome
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> have attributed the Cure to ſome of their intermixed Medicines, or alteration of the <hi>Doctors</hi> Bill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> He will avoid that incivility of ſuch of them, who in the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> preſence, will feel the Pulſe, judg of the Urine, diſcourſe the Cauſe, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, what the Diſeaſe is, and what will be the iſſue of it, propoſe Medicines, nay ſometimes endeavour to adviſe with the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> to contradict and diſpute with him, to compare and ſet himſelf above the
<hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician;</hi> and to ſay truth, theſe odious and intolerable Compariſons and intruſions daily complained of by my <hi>Collegues,</hi> were a great cauſe of my departing from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> He will avoid thoſe Scandals they have opportunity to raiſe, that ſuch a <hi>Phyſician</hi> is Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, Proud, Negligent, and minds not his practice, and the like without the leaſt ground, and are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently by ſuch Artifices, the Cauſe of introducing another
<hi>Phyſician,</hi> knowing that thereby more Bills will come to their File, and many times the former Medicines be layed aſide, and in this ſhuffling in and out of <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> they have commonly a great ſhare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly, Apothecaries</hi> being now Competitors with
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> for practice, and down-right Enemies to ſuch as make their own Medicines; why ſhould not we ſuſpect them of this falſe Play, by telling the <hi>Patient</hi> the <hi>Doctors</hi> Medicine will not work (which <pb n="33" facs="tcp:93631:16"/> he knows well enough how to effect) and then to tell him he will prepare him one of his own that will work, when perhaps that he calls his own preparation, was nothing but what the <hi>Doctor</hi> had preſcribed before; and by this Artifice to advance himſelf above the
<hi>Phyſician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another miſchief in ſending Bills to the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> is, that though the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> be honeſt (and who can tell which of them is ſo?) yet the Servants neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, or ignorance (to whom they commit the whole care of diſpenſing, and are intruth the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> (and not their Maſters) may mar all in their Maſters abſence, who is viſiting abroad, or at his recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>And now I have done with the unpleaſant taſk of raking into the faults of the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and with diſcourſing how
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> may ſave themſelves from their devices, I ſhall next ſhew the advantages that will come to the <hi>Patient,</hi> the
<hi>Phyſician,</hi> and people, by this way of remedy propoſed.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Patients,</hi> they may hereby ſave moſt of the great charges of <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Bills, which in long Caſes amount to very great ſums in a year, although the <hi>Phyſician</hi> hath received very few Fees; the <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> may ſo order his buſineſs as to take his Fee for his Viſits only, and at home ſuch competent Fees for his advice alone, as are uſually given, and in both Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes take nothing for his Medicines, and ſo ſave the <hi>Patient</hi> the whole charge of the
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> Bill, which very ſeldom comes ſhort, and for the moſt part manifoldly exceeds the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> Fees. And this he may very well do by making fewer, leſs chargable, <pb n="34" facs="tcp:93631:17"/> more effectual, and durable Medicines then the Shops afford, and ſuffer nothing in the non-uſe, or decay of his Medicines; becauſe he need make no more then will ſerve his own practice: and I muſt here profeſs, that which I intended not to have publiſhed, that this is the courſe I have generally taken, for the four Months laſt paſt, ſince I made my own Medicines, but that ſome <hi>Apothecaries</hi> have given out moſt falſly, that I have ſent in Bills to <hi>Patients</hi> for money; but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince ſuch of their wonted lying, I do hereby oblige my ſelf to give 100 <hi>pound</hi> to any of them that ſhall produce ſuch a Bill. <hi>Secondly,</hi> This way will not clog the <hi>Patient</hi> with more Medicines then are need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, nor will omit any thing may conduce to his reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, for if he fails in either,
'tis to his prejudice, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſpending more Medicines which coſt him mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or in not performing his Cure, which loſeth his practice.</p>
            <p>But I do not propoſe this courſe of mine as a general rule to all <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> but leave this to every mans pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate judgment; Neither do I hereby bind my ſelf to the ſame practice, becauſe ſome few Caſes may fall out (though to an equal advantage to the <hi>Patient</hi>) may perſwade me to the contrary. For I find ſome perſons of that perſwaſion, as to think they have not given ſatisfaction, unleſs they have payed for the Medicines; but to ſuch perſons, I have always allowed them to give me what they pleaſed themſelves, for the cure only, to the full ſatisfaction of both parties. Though I will not deny but ſome perſons out of gratitude for their Cure, have rewarded me beyond this propoſal. Some of my acquaintance have deſired me to be more
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93631:17"/> plain in this laſt Paragraph, eſpecially in that part of it where I ſay I do not bind my ſelf to the ſaid pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; and to declare more fully the Caſes that may perſwade me to the contrary; which are theſe and ſuch as theſe. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Where <hi>Patients</hi> of their own free offers will contract with the <hi>Phyſician<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly too meanly rewarded him for his Cure, in both which the Statutes of our <hi>College</hi> allow a contract to be made with <hi>Patients.</hi> Another caſe is, if a
<hi>Phyſician</hi> be conſulted once, and for his Fee hath given Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines
<hi>gratis,</hi> if the <hi>Patient</hi> frequently ſend for his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines without the leaſt reward at all. Or if the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient</hi> living far in the Country, having (as before) once conſulted the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> as in the laſt caſe, and ſhall for weeks, nay months, ſend for the ſame Medicines. Or if the <hi>Patients</hi> friend ſhall recommend a Medicine to another friend of his unknown to the <hi>Phyſician;</hi> and where he gives no Counſel, if a <hi>Phyſician</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſhall deſire ſome of his Medicines, which are all the caſes that occur at preſent; I ſay in ſome of theſe, the <hi>Phyſician</hi> muſt needs be payed for his Medicines; but in other, 'tis rational he ſhould be payed for his advice, as he deſireth new Medicines, which charge will be far ſhort alſo of the
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> Medicines, whether repeated or preſcribed upon new advice.</p>
            <p>Now the great charge of <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Bills, and nauſeouſneſs of their Medicines, appears to be the cauſe why long habitual diſeaſes, as the Kings Evil, Falling-Sickneſs, Convulſions, Melancholies, and Winds in the Bowels, Gouts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> become ſeldom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, though they may with a conſtant, facile way, be perfectly cured, where neither the great charge, <pb n="36" facs="tcp:93631:18"/> not unpleaſantneſs of Medicines, deterr them from a continued neceſſary uſe of Remedies. And for the ſame reaſons many will be kept from relapſes, who being tired out with taking variety of Medicines, give over before the tone and ſtrength of their parts is reſtored, which is neceſſary to be done in all long Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes.</p>
            <p>He may ſo contrive his Medicines, firſt, That they may be taken in ſmall quantity, and be made more grateful to the taſt, and ſtomach, and perform more then thoſe of the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> commonly ſlovenly made, and of themſelves Fulſom, Nauſeous, and Slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh. Secondly, His Medicines made for particular perſons, may laſt Weeks, Months, nay Years, whereas the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Drinks, eſpecially in the Summer time, muſt be renewed once, or twice every day, to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive charge of the <hi>Patient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That his Medicines may be fewer, is evident in
<hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians</hi> that practiſe in the Country, who ride far to
<hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients,</hi> and carry in their Mans Cloak-bag, Medicines enough, not only for the perſon he is ſent to, but alſo for moſt other perſons, and Caſes he meets with in his Travels, and therefore his Cloſet needs contain but few, yet noble and generous Medicines, and ſuch as may ſerve him upon all occaſions, ſupplying what's defective from the Fields or Gardens. He may avoid all pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous, uſeleſs, chargable Medicines of the Shops, and ſubſtitute in their place, cheaper, and more conducible to health; He may very well lay aſide the precious Stones, Saphir, Emerals,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> the high priced Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrals of Coral, and Pearl, made worſe by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratious, or rather deſtroyed thereby in their Virtue,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93631:18"/> as alſo Unicorns Horn, and Bezoar, all which are now rarely uſed alone, but in the received Compoſitions; He may alſo ſpare the charges of leaf-gold, for guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pots, Glaſſes, Pills, Electuaries, Boles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſerves only to raiſe the Bill.</p>
            <p>He may teach the <hi>Patients</hi> facile and eaſie Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as to make a Clyſter, apply Bliſters, or Medicines to the feet, where they are needful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in many Caſes may cure by well ordering his
<hi>Patient</hi> only, without any Remedies at all, or but very few, being free to act for the <hi>Patients</hi> Health, without the grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of the
<hi>Apothecary;</hi> and many other ways he may daily meet with, very advantageous to the <hi>Patient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He will have little uſe of Conſerves, Syrups, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hocks,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> a greater part whereof Sugar makes up, which doth more hurt to moſt perſons, then the other ingredients do good.</p>
            <p>As for Infuſions and Decoctions, he will find by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, how much liquor, or <hi>Menſiruum</hi> will ſuffice to extract the full vertue of the ingredients, and what are helps, or hinderances thereunto, and thereby neither ſuffer loſs in the quantity, or quality of them.</p>
            <p>He will diſcover the inefficacy of many of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rups and other Medicines in the Shops, made of ſuch ingredients, the qualities whereof, what with boiling, what with the great quantity of Sugar neceſſary to keep them, are either made uſeleſs, or oppoſite to the ends they are propoſed for. Eſpecially in ſuch Plants, Seeds, and Flowers, which conſiſt of fine vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latil parts, and even in drying and pounding, or the <pb n="38" facs="tcp:93631:19"/> leaſt boiling exhale and evaporate, and therefore in the common way of ordering them, loſe their whole ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or moſt of their efficacy, and alter in their proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. From which by ſeveral methods known to ſome
<hi>Phyſicians,</hi> very generous and ſingular Medicines may be produced.</p>
            <p>He need not uſe ſo large Compoſitions conſiſting of ſuch confuſed and contrary ingredients, and will find good reaſon to lay aſide thoſe unintelligible and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Compoſitions of Mithridate, and Treacle, and the ſo much magnified Treacle-water, and will ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute better in their places, of ſmaller charge, and leſs trouble; and this all <hi>Phyſicians</hi> I have converſed with, and the
<hi>College</hi> it ſelf, by their Book publiſhed for the common good, in the year before the Plague, and all thoſe <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in this City, who make or intend to make their own Medicines, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs.</p>
            <p>But here <hi>Apothecaries</hi> open wide, and cry out that the
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> are great Cheats, and envious perſons, for continuing ſuch flat Medicines, and not recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the World, or rather their Shops, our greater ſecrets. The anſwer is eaſie, that the Medicines in our <hi>Pharmacopaea,</hi> are the beſt of any other <hi>Pharmacopaea</hi> in the World, both for their goodneſs, and well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of them, whether they be Chymical, or Gale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical; and therefore the ſame ſcandal will ly on all
<hi>Pharmacopaea's</hi> whatſoever. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſay that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe few laſt experimental years, the practical part of Phyſic hath been much improved (as well as Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy) eſpecially by ſuch as have put their hands to work; and therefore till ſuch improvement, this could
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93631:19"/> not be well amended. Furthermore, in making new Diſpenſatories, a full conſent muſt be had, and 'twere not fit to move where the motion were not like to take place, for though private men invent new ways of compounding and preparing, and uſing their own invented Medicines, yet 'twill require a long time to make them publickly known, and brought into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe, and till that be done 'tis not poſſible to have them brought into a common Diſpenſatory; beſides, no man would make a motion for ſuch a reformation, unleſs he were well furniſhed with ſpecificks, and then 'twill be required of him to expoſe them to the whole World, which how incongruous it will be, every man may eaſily conceive; hereto add, that the
<hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> think themſelves able enough by this preſent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſatory, to out-beard <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and do publickly profeſs (as hath been ſaid) that they underſtand the practice of Phyſic as well as they; how much more would they have ſaid ſo, if they had been made Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of theſe ſecrets? And here I ſhall admoniſh thoſe of my own Faculty, who have devoted their Studies, Labours, and Purſes, for the improvement of their Art, to conſider, that as natural things have their bounds and limits, and that there is no new Creation of them, and beſides, that theſe things have their bounds alſo of improvement, beyond which 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for man to go; and that by a good method and induſtry, that end may be attained; (though at preſent I muſt confeſs, no Art is more capable of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement then ours:) I ſay let all conſider, and they will find, what a vaſt encouragement they have to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their knowledg ſo far, that they ſhall not only be <pb n="40" facs="tcp:93631:20"/> able to leave mankind deſtitute of no remedy Nature did ever produce; but alſo reſtore and ſetle thoſe Honours ignorant men would uſurp, upon the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Profeſſors of this Science; and I ſee no reaſon why
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> ſhould communicate their ſecrets to ſuch perſons, who will make uſe of them, to the ruine of the Inventors, which is indeed a failer of truſt, for when a <hi>Phyſician</hi> writes his Bill, he truſts the <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary</hi> only with making the Medicine for a particular occaſion, and not to make uſe of it as his own when he pleaſeth for his own profit, and the Inventor have no further benefit by it, then perhaps one ſingle advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> When Diſpenſatories were firſt made, the
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> were really <hi>Phyſicians</hi> Servants, and wholy at their command, not in the leaſt intrenching on their buſineſs, and the rates of Medicines were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable; which ſuperiority over them ſtill continues only in their preſcriptions, the forms whereof are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways commanding to take this and that, and to mix them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but within theſe few laſt years they have ſet up for themſelves, and advanced the rates beyond all reaſon; and to be ſure, the more we teach them by our Books, the more they will trangreſs in both.</p>
            <p>He may receive encouragement from what he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, that is more then ordinarily uſeful, whereas by writing Bills, he ſoon communicates to the ignorant and lazy, who will neither ſpend time nor money to advance the Art, but while the one is at work to his great charge, loſs of time, much pains and trouble, the others ſeek by petty tricks and Arts to gain a name,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93631:20"/> and profit from the induſtrious. Nay ſome
<hi>Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks</hi> have been ſet up by purchaſing receipts of the
<hi>Apothecary</hi> or his Servants. And one of them told me, he ſet up a
<hi>Quack</hi> by ſelling and commending to him a Medicine he had long kept in his Shop and could not otherwiſe put off, and that by degrees he made him a famous practiſer among the ignorant and poor people. An Act quite contrary to the intereſt of the Company.</p>
            <p>Hence alſo will ariſe an emulation amongſt
<hi>Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who ſhall exceed each other in noble remedies, and from thence a full and happy improvement of whatſoever God hath created for the recovery of mans health impaired; for from the <hi>Phyſician</hi> alone the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Phyſic is to be expected. How many ſimples of unknown properties have been brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to uſe, to the great comfort of the ſick? and many more may be, as alſo many preparations, both ſimple and compound, both in the Galenical, and Chymical practice, and by this means the Art will be advanced to its juſt dignity, now much diminiſhed, diſhonoured, and near to be loſt by the intruſion of ignorant perſons.</p>
            <p>Greater reſpect will be given to ſuch <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> as being the immediate inſtruments of life and health, who will derive unto themſelves that which is now given to the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> which proceeds chiefly from fear leſt they ſhould do the <hi>Patient</hi> hurt; and ſo their honour will be doubled, which every <hi>Phyſician</hi> looks principally at; but the <hi>Apothecary</hi> being not ſo far concerned, looks chiefly at his own profit, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards not the <hi>Patients</hi> charge. For the greater the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients</hi> 
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:93631:21"/> charge, the greater muſt needs be the <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> gain; whereas on the contrary, 'tis the <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> Intereſt to cure the <hi>Patient</hi> with the greateſt eaſe.</p>
            <p>He may proceed on ſafely and ſecurely in his well experienced Medicines, having before him not only what he hath preſcribed for the ſame
<hi>Patient,</hi> but for all others in the like Caſe, and thereby keep in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory what he would have forgot, if his Bill had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained on the
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> File; <hi>viz.</hi> the Medicines and their ſucceſs. By means whereof <hi>Phyſicians</hi> do not advance their knowledg ſo far as they might; for how is it poſſible they ſhould remember the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of their Bills writ ſome days before? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore know not how to proceed ſo well. But the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> having before them the whole ſeries of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, brag they can do more then the
<hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and by this means inſinuate the ſame opinion into people.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Phyſician</hi> will be conſulted in the beginning of Diſeaſes, to the ſafety and little expence of the <hi>Patient,</hi> who will not go firſt to the <hi>Apothecary,</hi> who practiſeth on him till the Caſe is deſperate, and then calls in a <hi>Phyſician</hi> when 'tis too late; and if he dyes, the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician</hi> muſt carry away the diſgrace alone; but if he recover, the <hi>Apothecary,</hi> if he be ſo minded, by ſome trick will ſhare with him in the honour: and by this reſort of people to the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> in beginning of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, we meet with few Caſes of eaſie Cure, but are chiefly made uſe of in dangerous Diſeaſes, or thoſe of ſhort period, or ſuch as are accompanyed with great pains and torments, to our great and continual anxiety.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:93631:21"/>The <hi>Phyſicians</hi> experience hereby as
'tis ſurer, ſo 'twill be greater.</p>
            <p>He will make uſe of no Medicines but the choiceſt, and when they are in their full vigour, and ſuch as are durable, and after once or twice Tryal of them, will ſeldom fail in his expected ſucceſs; which cannot be certainly had without ſome tryal. For though a man buy the choiceſt ingredients, <hi>viz. Sena,</hi> which may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the Senſes very good, yet he cannot poſitively ſay, how well, nor yet what quantity of it will work, till he hath made uſe of it. But afterwards he may confidently apply the whole parcel he hath bought to his purpoſe. The like may be inſtanced in a crop of Wheat or Barley, which the ſkillfulleſt Huſband-man cannot tell how they will yield for Bread, or Malt, till he hath uſed them. Now how is it poſſible that a <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician</hi> can with any certainty make uſe of ſeveral Shops, ſince there is ſo great difference in the ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents? and 'tis certain the ſame Medicine made by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> ſhall differ much in colour, ſmell, and taſt, and conſequently effect too; which cannot proceed from any other cauſe then the difference of the ingredients themſelves, or by omitting ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients, or by ſubſtituting one thing for another; or by diſtinct ways of preparing them. The ſame alſo may be ſaid of Compoſitions, much more of Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Medicines ſo much ſophiſticated, and of ſo much danger and hazard, if not well prepared, which he cannot diſcover till he hath ſeen the effect of them, unleſs it be ſuch as he makes himſelf, nor thoſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till he hath made ſome tryal of them.</p>
            <p>He will much inlarge <hi>Materia Medica,</hi> Chymiſtry
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:93631:22"/> and Pharmacy, and diſcover the grounds of them, and wherein the efficacy of remedies lyes, and thereby lay open a whole Ocean for new diſcoveries, and by the by obſerve many uſeful products and Phaenomena of Nature, to the great improvement of his Art, and ſound Natural Philoſophy, which are not taken notice of by <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and their Servants; for all which they have neither will nor ſkill.</p>
            <p>As to the improvement of Medicines, this may be added, by the experimenting <hi>Phyſician,</hi> that in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd waters he will conſider and find which of them will afford any virtue, which only phlegm equivalent but to Conduit-water, which of them will keep long, and in perfection, which ſoon or in what time decay, and ſpend them accordingly, and in compound di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd waters, will find cauſe to lay aſide many ſimples as nothing conducing, or rather weakning the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of the Medicine deſigned; whereby much charge and trouble will be ſpared, and better compoſitions be made.</p>
            <p>He will gain and keep to himſelf <hi>Patients,</hi> who have diſeaſes they are unwilling ſhould be known by <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> and their Boys, and all ſuch as have a mind to turn over their File.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Patient</hi> will have better opinion of the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and confidence in the uſe of them, and the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician</hi> be more ſatisfied in his Conſcience, and better aſſured of the ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>He will gain reputation to his Art, by reſtoring it to its firſt inſtitution and practice, by the Founders and Heroes of Phyſic.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:93631:22"/>'Tis convenient to adjoin here the old way of educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting young men into the practice of Phyſic, and ſurely the ſafer for the Patients health; and I could wiſh 'twere reſtored to its former uſage, which was this. The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior <hi>Phyſician</hi> carried his Son, or ſuch as he intended to ſucceed him in his practice, along with him when he viſited his Patients, diſcovering, and diſcourſing with them the diſeaſe, cauſe, method of cure, and what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies were fit to be applied to the preſent Caſe, and to try them what they would do in that or the like Caſe. And when his occaſions would not permit him to viſit himſelf, he then ſent one of his Scholars to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him of the condition of the ſick perſon, and the effect of his Medicines; and alſo when the ſaid Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars had leiſure, they were employ'd to help to gather, prepare, and make, or overſee the compounding of Medicines. And ſuch Scholars they call'd
<hi>filii Artis,</hi> ſons of Art. Some of the Profeſſors in Foreign parts practiſe the moſt of this to this very day, with ſuch Gentlemen as travel thither to ſtudy Phyſic, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their reading with experience.</p>
            <p>By conſtantly practiſed Medicines he will find out a better method of Cure, and may hereby arrive at the true cauſes of diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>He will obſerve what Medicines by precipitation or other ways, alter, deſtroy, or weaken one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whereby of good ingredients ſingly uſed, a bad Compoſition may be made, and therefore fail in the ſucceſs expected. Many more things might be here added, which a ſkillful obſerver, and verſed in the way to make experiments (no eaſie matter) will daily find, and at preſent I do not ſo much as give hints of them,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93631:23"/> but ſhall hereafter, as occaſion and opportunity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>He will have more ſcope to be charitable to the poor, and more civil and obliging to his friends, by curing them <hi>gratis,</hi> of at ſmall charges.</p>
            <p>He need not trouble himſelf with ways of conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the uſe of his Medicines, by ſetting down no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in his Bill, but giving them to the <hi>Patient,</hi> which the <hi>Apothecary</hi> ſoon learns; nor with giving ſome of his own Medicines at a pinch, which if they ſucceed not, to be ſure the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> will cry down in all places, but will conceal all eminently good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, as diſadvantageous to themſelves; nor by placing their <hi>Arcana's</hi> in the Shops of thoſe
<hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> they commonly make uſe of; nor by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending their
<hi>Patients</hi> to ſuch <hi>Apothecaries</hi> they intruſt their ſecrets with. For then great complaints are made that the
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> carry away their Cuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and take away their livelyhood, affirming they are willing to fetch them from the preſcribing
<hi>Doctors Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries.</hi> To which I anſwer, that they do fetch them, but perhaps not always; ſince I have heard them often ſay, theſe ſecrets were but the Medicines of the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Diſpenſatory diſguiſed under new names, to the diſcredit of the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> that preſcribed them. And I well remember ſome of them have neglected to fetch from my houſe, not far from their own, ſome of my preparations, though they had them <hi>gratis,</hi> for the fetching; whereby the
<hi>Patients</hi> have ſuffered, and thought I neglected them, 'till they were rectified by another Viſit. Nay one of them told me, he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dy with his own Shop-Medicines, then be cured <pb n="47" facs="tcp:93631:23"/> with my Magiſtrals: much more would he have ſaid of <hi>Patients,</hi> manifeſtly preferring his own profit before their lives; a moſt Unchriſtian ſaying!</p>
            <p>One ſingular advantage ſuch a <hi>Phyſician</hi> will have, that the ſlanders of the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> will appear to be malicious, as being raiſed againſt ſuch as act contrary to their profit.</p>
            <p>By this means <hi>Phyſicians</hi> will unite againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy, will contribute mutual aſſiſtance, and communicate more freely to one another their practice and remedies; and alſo the frauds and unlawful pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> will conceal the counſels, and act whatſoever may tend to the advance of their Art; and
<hi>Patients</hi> alſo will diſcover the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> cenſures, and practices againſt the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> and their preſcriptions.</p>
            <p>Hereby that great intereſt will decay <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> have in Families for their petty officiouſneſſes (which
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> not to diſpleaſe them have put them upon) theſe will be taught Nurſes, and the aſſiſtants, and which are by ſome of theſe as well, certainly more diligently performed then by the
<hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereby the <hi>filii Artis,</hi> or younger <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> will ſooner come into a better and more ſetled practice, and not be beholden to <hi>Apothecaries</hi> to bring them <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients</hi> wherewith they often upbraid them, and glory amongſt themſelves and to other perſons, that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced ſuch and ſuch a <hi>Phyſician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereby <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> will be reſtored to ſome of their employment now uſurped by the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> as let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of blood, applying Leeches, Plaſters, Cupping-Glaſſes, <pb n="48" facs="tcp:93631:24"/> Syringing and Salivation, wraping up bodies in Cere-Cloaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which indeed do more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belong to them then to the
<hi>Apothecaries;</hi> hereby alſo haply many occaſions of quarrel betwixt
<hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians</hi> and the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> will ceaſe, each party act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to his own way.</p>
            <p>By this means Pſeudochymiſts, and other <hi>Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks</hi> mouths and revilings will be ſtopped, only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming for this, that
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> make not their own Medicines. But ſince the publication of theſe papers I am informed that the ſaid Pſeudochymiſts and
<hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks</hi> rail againſt me, this Book, and the way pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, as much as the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> though before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Enemies each to others. So that they have fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Proverb, of <hi>like to like.</hi> And no wonder ſince hereby their Kingdom of darkneſs is brought to light, and they are obliged to oppoſe it, as the Copper-Smiths were to revile St.
<hi>Paul</hi> for ſpeaking againſt the Idol of <hi>Diana</hi> of the
<hi>Epheſians,</hi> whereby their trade was loſt.</p>
            <p>And as for the reaſonableneſs of it, that the
<hi>Phyſician</hi> ought to ſupport himſelf by all lawful ways and means, and to have praeeminence above thoſe ignorant perſons that incroach upon his profeſſion, 'tis confeſſed by all that have conſidered the great charge, ſtudy, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, before he can arrive at any benefit from it; for he muſt take the chargeable degrees of Batchellor, and Maſter of Arts, Batchellor of Phyſic, and after 14 years ſtanding, the degree of
<hi>Doctor;</hi> beſides his bare expences for his maintenance in the Univerſity, Charges in Anatomies, knowledg of natural things; Travels abroad, Chymiſtry, and Experiments; his <pb n="49" facs="tcp:93631:24"/> Library, Habit, his more free way of living in a ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table houſe, and Attendants, greater Taxes,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that a <hi>Doctor</hi> of Phyſic ſpends more before he comes to practiſe, then will ſet up perhaps a dozen
<hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> in a way of livelihood; and beſides, great ſums of money before he can put himſelf in a fitting Equipage: whereas on the contrary, many young men before their time of Apprenticeſhip is out, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide well for themſelves by Quacking; and certainly the Study of Phyſic, and conſequently the knowledge of Nature, muſt bid farewel to the Univerſities, if Shops be permitted to make practiſers, for ſuch the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will ſoon create <hi>Doctors,</hi> which title the
<hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> takes upon him, though he underſtand not the reaſon of the name, to the great ſhame of the Univerſities, and Faculty, when ignorant people ſhall give, and they challenge the ſame title for nothing, attained by the <hi>Phyſician</hi> at a great rate and long ſtudy, the vulgar ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Practiſer and <hi>Doctor</hi> to ſignifie the ſame thing. And which no perſons of knowledge and education do, and perhaps moſt other perſons give them in way of Jeering.</p>
            <p>From the handſom ſupport of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> theſe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits will accrue to the publick, that thereby the honour all Nations yield to the Engliſh <hi>Phyſicians</hi> will be kept up, who in the late times, when the reputation of the Nation was well neer forfeited abroad, the
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> then in being, moſt whereof are now living, and Members of the <hi>College,</hi> maintained the credit, for learning and value, of this Kingdom, and ſince his Majeſties happy return, ſome of them have kept up the honour of the Faculty; which manifeſtly appears <pb n="50" facs="tcp:93631:25"/> by the great eſteem Foreigners have of their Books, by often printing them, and tranſlating into Latin what hath been publiſhed in Engliſh, though they are no where ſo depreſſed as in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond benefit to the publick is, that men of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Eſtates will breed up their Sons in the Art of Phyſic, giving them ſuch education as is neceſſary, and will not vouchſafe to place them out to
<hi>Apothecaries,</hi> though now adays want of learning and degrees are adjudged as needful a qualification for the exerciſe of Phyſic, as formerly
'twas for Preaching, and the Shops fit to ſupply both.</p>
            <p>I will conclude this part of my diſcourſe with this obſervation; that the Laws of <hi>England</hi> in all their Acts of Parliament, have granted the practice of Phyſic to <hi>Phyſicians</hi> and them alone, and in no clauſe thereof put in any reſtraint at all upon them, but every where, either new priviledges, or a confirmation of the old, have been granted, by the ſaid powers. Whereas on the contrary, the Law ſuppoſeth cheats in the <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> Shops, and therefore impowers our <hi>Cenſors</hi> to deſtroy and burn what they find bad and corrupt.</p>
            <p>The next thing to be treated of, ſhall be the ways of
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> creeping into practice, and their unfitneſs thereunto. As to the firſt, heretofore when they were Members of the Company of Grocers, and diſperſed in place, as well as in counſel, they then were wholy ſubordinate to the <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> only keeping in their Shops, and faithfully making the preſcriptions they received from the
<hi>Phyſician,</hi> and when made, ſending them to the <hi>Patient</hi> by their men (as they ſtill continue to do in Foreign Countries) and not committing the <pb n="51" facs="tcp:93631:25"/> preparation to raw Boys, or Apprentices, which is the true intereſt of the <hi>Patient</hi> they ſhould do here like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. But in proceſs of time, <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in acute di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes having taught them ſomewhat, ſent them to viſit their
<hi>Patients,</hi> to give them the beſt account they could of the eſtate of their health, and effect of their Medicines. And of later years ſome
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> took them along with them in their Viſits, whereby they acquired a little ſmattering of diſeaſes, by which means, and their continual officiouſneſs, they inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves into Families, and by applying (right or wrong) the terms of Art they had learned from the
<hi>Phyſicians,</hi> they made people believe they had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired ſome ſkill in the Art, and afterwards began to venture a little at practice, and but until theſe 10 years laſt paſt kept themſelves within ſome bounds and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits; but ſince that time have daily more and more incroached upon our Profeſſion, being aſſiſted by a greater familiarity of converſation with younger <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians.</hi> And in the Plague time they took upon them the whole Practice of Phyſic, which ever ſince they have continued, being much helped alſo therein by the diſperſing of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> into places unknown to their <hi>Patients,</hi> by the Fire, but above all by the burning of the <hi>College,</hi> by means whereof their Government and view of their Shops have been omitted, inſomuch that now they are paſt all reſtraint, having inſinuated and (as they think) rooted themſelves by the aforeſaid Artifices, ſo that there remains now no other real re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy but that propoſed.</p>
            <p>Now here I ſhall take occaſion in a ſhort digreſſion, to diſcourſe briefly the reaſon, why in all Ages there <pb n="52" facs="tcp:93631:26"/> have been ſo many pretenders to Phyſic, and why ſome of them have got reputation in the World. One hath been mentioned before, <hi>viz.</hi> the great charges ſick men are put to, cauſed by the ſeparation of the
<hi>Phyſician</hi> from the <hi>Apothecary.</hi> But the principal reaſon is, the want of knowledge in moſt perſons, both of the materials uſed, and the grounds for which they are applyed. Inſomuch that there are but few that can judg, and diſtinguiſh rightly of either, and no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der therefore that in their reaſonings they commit more abſurd miſtakes, or Paralogiſms then in any other Art whatſoever, and cenſure
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> by the ſucceſs alone. Which my Lord <hi>Verulam</hi> accounts the great unhappineſs both of the Stateſ-man and the
<hi>Phyſician,</hi> both being alike cenſured by thoſe that know not the bottom and riſe of their Actions and Counſels. For how can any man in either make a ſound Judgment without a full knowledge of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs it ſelf, and of all the circumſtances thereunto belonging; nor in Phyſic without the concurrent knowledg of the ſick mans habit, diſeaſe, cauſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, and many other particulars neceſſary to make a clear judgment upon the ſucceſs? Yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, many will cenſure and grumble at the actions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Stateſ-men, though their proceedings have been never ſo wiſe, and prudent, and oft-times from mutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and whiſpering, fall to down-right diſtaſt, and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny againſt their Superiors. So that the good ſucceſs, in State-affairs, of raſh and imprudent undertakers, have been extolled and preferred before the wary, and prudent management, and guidance of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bereſt and wiſeſt Stateſ-men. The ſame likewiſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:93631:26"/> happens between the bold <hi>Empiric,</hi> and learnedſt
<hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician.</hi> But in this way of cenſuring, the Stateſ-man hath this advantage above the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> that 'tis poſſible he may meet with a ſeries of Buſineſs ſo cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantiated, as ſeldom or never to miſcarry, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially having a greater power over ſubordinate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then <hi>Phyſicians</hi> have. But the irreverſible ſtatute of Heaven forbids us to expect a conſtant recovery of our <hi>Patients,</hi> for
'tis appointed, that all men muſt die. 'Tis ſufficient therefore for us, to employ thoſe remedies God hath given to the Sons of men, to the utmoſt vertue the Creator hath endowed them withal: ſince his eternal decree hath limited their efficacy from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king man immortal. Now ſince (if men judg by the ſucceſs alone) it cannot be otherwiſe, but that the moſt learned
<hi>Phyſician,</hi> and moſt ſottiſh <hi>Empiric</hi> muſt be thought equal in ſkill, by thoſe that are not able to make a right judgment and difference betwixt them on other principles. Hence it comes to paſs, that where ſome ignorant perſon hath cured accidentally a ſlight diſeaſe, and a <hi>Phyſician</hi> hath a <hi>Patient</hi> dye of an irrecoverable Caſe, here the <hi>Empiric</hi> ſhall be applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the
<hi>Phyſician</hi> decryed. Nay many will ſay the diſeaſe is the ſame in both, whereas we daily ſee moſt groſs miſtakes in ſuch opinions, when the Caſes differ totally in their Nature, agreeing in one ſign only common to both the Caſes propoſed, nay to many other alſo. Furthermore, if a <hi>Patient</hi> dy under an <hi>Empirics</hi> hand, the friends willingly conceal their Names, leſt ſome diſcredit ſhould befal them for uſing ſuch worthleſs practiſers; but if under the hands of a known
<hi>Phyſician,</hi> he ſhall be ſure to be named, and <pb n="54" facs="tcp:93631:27"/> ſometimes his attendance falſly fathered on him, when
<hi>Mountebanks</hi> only have been employed: but to beſure if an
<hi>Empirie</hi> hath firſt been made uſe of, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an able
<hi>Phyſician</hi> called in (when all opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of doing good was paſt) and the <hi>Patient</hi> dy, the <hi>Mountebank</hi> hath never been mentioned, but the <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> perhaps condemned, though he hath done whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever could have been thought on, rational in that Caſe.</p>
            <p>Add to the former reaſons, the bold and confident brags, and promiſes of <hi>Empirics,</hi> that they have cured worſe diſeaſes, and will in few hours free them from their maladies, eſpecially where ſober
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> have pronounced doubtfully of the event. No wonder that theſe pleaſing promiſes to perſons in danger and diſtreſs bring them into employment even with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the former ſober
<hi>Phyſician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, a fooliſh opinion prevails with ſome igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant perſons, that they will deal only with ſuch as will undertake the Cure, (that is) contract with them for a ſum of money, one half whereof to be payed in hand, and the other the Cure being done, and ſo are uſually cheated of one half of their money; and ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will have nothing to do with ſuch
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> as will not undertake them in this ſence.</p>
            <p>Another Stratagem is, to give ſtrange and hard names to their Medicines, ſuch as are <hi>Pilulae radiis Solis extractae,</hi> and in Engliſh is no more then Pills dryed to that conſiſtence by the Sun-Beams, which ignorant people have thought were made of the Sun Beams. Others commend their Extract of the Soul of the Heathen Gods. One ſets up with a receipt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from <hi>Van Helmonts</hi> own hands; Another hath
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:93631:27"/> received from a Jew the ſhining of <hi>Moſes</hi> Face; nay I have heard a Pſeudochymiſt blaſphemouſly brag, he ſaw in the making of a grand <hi>Elixir,</hi> the Quinteſſence of the Trinity in Unity, and infinite other pitiful cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivations of ſilly people, to be ſeen on every Gate and Poſt of this City; ſuch as are the Spirit of the Salt of the World, <hi>Panchymagogon,</hi> and other ten-footed Greek names, and ſome other Mongrel non-ſenſical ones compounded of ſeveral Languages; promiſing certain, ſpeedy, and concealed Cure of incurable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes.</p>
            <p>And no leſs ridiculous and abſurd to conſidering perſons are, their cantings of themſelves, wherewith they no leſs befool, amuſe, and beguile the people; as that by long prayer, and ſeeking of God, they have had many ſecrets revealed to them from Heaven. Another by long Travels through <hi>Hungary, Poland,</hi> &amp;c. hath attained great ſecrets from Kings and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. Another a Gentleman lately come from <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> or
<hi>Cambridg,</hi> Cures the Pox, Running of the Reins, &amp;c. in Capital Letters, at all which what ſober man cannot but laugh? Yet ſuch as theſe are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements to many to reſort to them; moreover ſome of them are Aſtrologers, Phyſiognomers, Fortune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellers, Profeſſors of Palmiſtry and ſuch other vain Arts, much applauded by the weaker ſort of people.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the former they have their Emiſſaries, Scouts, and Setters up and down, to cry up the ſkill and feigned Cures done by them, Nurſes, Good-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, Midwives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to make up the cry and full noiſe.</p>
            <p>Now it being natural to moſt people to admire what
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93631:28"/> they underſtand not, and for Admiration to infer Love, and Love Praiſe, and Praiſe the uſe eſpecially of ſuch things as are ſet off with high and lofty expreſſions, it neceſſarily follows that ſuch perſons will cry up, and make uſe of, thoſe that by theſe means captivate their underſtandings, eſpecially their credits being ingaged alſo; but above all, if they proceed from meaner perſons, of whom they are moſt credulous, having in ſuſpition wiſermen, believing the former are not able, and that the wiſer are able; and therefore will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them. All which appears in ſome with us cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up above any <hi>Phyſician</hi> that ever was in <hi>England,</hi> though for pitiful, dangerous, nay ſometimes mortal Medicines, whereby great ſums of money have been gained in a ſhort time. I ſhall inſtance firſt in <hi>Lockyers</hi> Pills made of
<hi>Antimony,</hi> diſcovered to be ſo by ſome of my <hi>Collegues,</hi> and my ſelf, at the firſt ſelling of them. A Medicine as ill made as any of that Mineral, and no <hi>Phyſician</hi> though meanly verſed in Chymiſtry, but could have excelled it. Yet ſo great a Vogue this Pill had for ſome time, that infinite people reſorted to him, and purchaſed them for their lives, both for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and Families, and (as I have heard) for their poſterities too. Though a common Chimney in a little time would have made enough of it to have ſerved the whole Nation for ſome years to come, and that at very ſmall charges. But Experience, the Tutor of too many, hath in a ſhort time brought theſe Pills into a diſ-uſe, if not a total Oblivion, even amongſt the vulgar.</p>
            <p>A ſecond cryed up Medicine was <hi>Mathews</hi>'s Pills, made of
<hi>Opium</hi> (to which the virtue of the whole <pb n="57" facs="tcp:93631:28"/> Compoſition muſt be attributed) of white <hi>Hellebor</hi> Roots, and Oyl of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> whereto ſome add Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> which will puzzle the moſt knowing Naturaliſt to declare why theſe ſhould be thus jumbled together; unleſs to obſcure the <hi>Opium.</hi> 'Tis indeed a very cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Compoſition, for by giving reſt and eaſe it may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily decoy people into the uſe of them, though by long taking of them, diſeaſes become far more uncurable then they are in their own Nature.</p>
            <p>A third Univerſal Medicine was <hi>Hughes</hi>'s Powder, ſold by him at 10<hi>s.</hi> the Grain, and 3<hi>l.</hi> 10<hi>s.</hi> the Doſe, made doubtleſs of Gold and Quickſilver. The taſt and weight of it manifeſtly diſcover the former to be an ingredient into it, and the effect,
<hi>viz.</hi> Salivation proves the latter to be part of the compound. Beſides I have made of theſe two diſſolved, and digeſted in their peculiar Menſtruums, in no long ſpace of time, a Medicine that had the ſame effect with his, and in the ſame Doſe; and having a View of his Cabinet left after his Death, containing a large quantity of the ſaid Powder (being all he left behind him) there was found crude Gold, and Quickſilver in the ſame Cabinet. Now theſe three Notorious Univerſal Medicines were put to ſale by moſt ignorant perſons. Add here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the forementioned <hi>Mr. De-laun's</hi> Pill, whereof I ſhall ſay nothing, being mentioned under the Name of the <hi>Pilulae ex duobus,</hi> in the <hi>London Diſpenſatory,</hi> though ſome make them of the Extract of
<hi>Coloquintida.</hi> The laſt of any Fame with us, were Dr.
<hi>Goddard</hi>'s Drops, a good Medicine, but not ſo univerſal, and ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive as he would have made the World believe, and was nothing elſe but what ſome <hi>Phyſicians</hi> many years <pb n="58" facs="tcp:93631:29"/> ſince enjoyed. I well remember that in the late troubles, a Perſon then in great Authority, having cryed up this above all the Medicines in the World, a round wager was offered, that the <hi>Doctor</hi> ſhould not diſtinguiſh his own from two others that ſhould be brought him, both which were but Spirit of
<hi>Harts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn.</hi> But the wager would not be accepted of. Furthermore, that this Medicine of his was Spirit of <hi>Harts-horn,</hi> ſome relations plainly argue; One where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was the following.</p>
            <p>A certain perſon in <hi>Norfolk</hi> having ſent for as much as came to a 11<hi>l.</hi> and dying upon the 2<hi>d.</hi> doſe of it, and by accident moſt part of the remainder being ſpilt; there comes in a friend to the Houſe, of ſome ſkill, who ſuppoſing it to be Spirit of
<hi>Harts-horn,</hi> told the Widow he would endeavour to gain back the money for her. And thereupon went to a Chymiſt, and bought as much of the ſaid Spirit, as would make up the quantity purchaſed of Dr. <hi>Goddard,</hi> who after Tryal of it by ſmell, and taſt, acknowledged it to be his, and honeſtly payed back the ſum 'twas firſt ſold for; which I think few of the <hi>Mountebanks</hi> do. Sure I am that a Quack ſold 21 Pills for
20<hi>l.</hi> whereof the <hi>Patient</hi> took 4 at two doſes, to the great hazard of his life, who then repairing to me for my advice, I by Tryal of one of them ſound them to be Mercurial, and wiſhed him to return them back, but the Quack would not give him 10<hi>s.</hi> for the 16 remaining.</p>
            <p>The inference and ſum of what hath been ſaid, is to ſhew briefly by what Artifices people are deceived in their Healths, and Purſes, and how eaſily the ignorant are couzened, and ſuch practices uſed, that
<hi>Phyſicians,</hi> 
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:93631:29"/> men of honeſty and repute, would be aſhamed to own, and muſt by uſing them in a ſhort time be ruined and diſcredited. And ſuch Cheats as theſe, the <hi>College</hi> of
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> are bound by the Laws of the Land to decry, and puniſh (though by ſo doing it hath often incurred the cenſure and clamor of the vulgar) Beſides the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the 14<hi>th.</hi> and 15<hi>th.</hi> of
<hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns us to it, declaring that 'tis good for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of this Realm, and therefore expedient, and neceſſary to provide that no perſon of the <hi>College</hi> of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> (for all practiſers then were of the ſaid body) be ſuffered to exerciſe, and practiſe Phyſic, but only thoſe perſons that be profound, ſad, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, groundly learned, and deeply ſtudyed in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſic. Now certain it is, that none of the ſaid body did or dare uſe any of the forementioned frauds and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, but will conſtantly indeavour (ſince 'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but there will be Cheatees; (according to the old Proverb,
<hi>Populus vult decipi, The People will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi>) to abridge the number of the Cheaters, who anſwer to the former part of the Proverb,
<hi>Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piatur, Let them be couzened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall end this diſcourſe by returning from my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion to the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> who may and do uſe ſome of the tricks before-mentioned, and ſhall here briefly recite ſome great advantages they have, and make uſe of above <hi>Phyſicians.</hi> One is, that they live in this City 7 or 8 years as <hi>Apprentices,</hi> as alſo by their retail Trade, and by living in open Shops, by frequent converſe with their fellow Citizens, whether in Commerce or Offices, by many friendly and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly mutual kindneſſes and actions, wherein they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:93631:30"/> ſpend their whole lives, and are never diverted by ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and ingenuity from their propoſed way of gain, by all which means they get into a fixed familiarity and good opinion with their Neighbours, and a large acquaintance in the World. Now for their ſkill, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what hath been before-mentioned, and common to them with the <hi>Mountebank, viz.</hi> Vapouring and braging of their ſkill, and decrying <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> by talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing above the Capacity of thoſe they converſe with, who therefore take all they ſay to be authentick, though never ſo abſurd, and trivial, and many times to ſet off themſelves they will venture to ſpeak Latine commonly as falſe as the matter, although ſome of them at
<hi>Coffee-Houſes,</hi> and in other mixt Companies, by venturing ſo boldly have been met with and baffled, and made to depart thence with ſhame and diſcredit enough, which their friends and acquaintance take little notice of. Add hereunto their expoſing to view their Compoſitions of <hi>Treacle, Mithridate, Diaſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> and <hi>Alkermes,</hi> which all their friends, and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours one time of another muſt ſee; (being ſet off by ſome very curiouſly) and ſeeing cannot but admire the great charge, art, and labour of the <hi>Apothecary,</hi> and perhaps hear his learned Lecture upon them, whereby they imply their great ſkill, knowledg in the virtues of theſe ingredients, and conſequently an ability to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe with them; all which are below the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a <hi>Phyſician;</hi> and therefore a long time is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for him to gain acquaintance, wanting the fore-mentioned opportunities the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> enjoy.
<hi>Laſtly,</hi> Their painted Pots and Glaſſes, with falſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:93631:30"/> Titles on them, more win the vulgar then a
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> Library of far greater value.</p>
            <p>As to their incapacity for Practice, 'tis manifeſt by their education, and ignorance of all thoſe things which are required in an able
<hi>Phyſician, viz.</hi> the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Arts and Languages; by the former whereof men learn the way and rules of obſerving, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements to be made thereon; by the latter, what the learned ſearchers of Nature have in all Ages ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, neceſſary, and little enough in an Art ſo difficult as that of Phyſic. They are wholy igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant alſo of all Philoſophy, and the very Elements of the Art, and therefore unſkillful in knowing diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and more ſurely their cauſes, whereto reſpect is to be had, as well as to the diſeaſes, to which, fit remedies are to be applyed. For want of Anatomy know neither the part affected, nor how 'tis affected; much leſs any thing of Chirurgical directions. And through their ignorance in Philoſophy, and Arts, they have not ſkill enough to adviſe a diet ſutable to diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, a thing moſt neceſſary, as well in curing diſeaſes as in preſerving of health, and which requires a great inſight into the nature of things; nor the true grounds and reaſons of compounding, practiſing their way ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by rote then by rule; with better reaſon may a Brick-layer or Carpenter pretend to be a Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, or a Common Fidler to be a Muſick Reader in the Univerſities, or
<hi>Greſham-College,</hi> ſince both theſe have the practical part of thoſe Sciences, which <hi>Apothecaries</hi> have not in Phyſic, in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>And to conceal their miſ-actings, they generally do
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:93631:31"/> all by word of mouth, and not enter their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions into their Books, being haply aſhamed any knowing men ſhould diſcover their ſins of omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as dangerous many times in point of life and health, as thoſe of their commiſſion. Whereas <hi>Phyſicians</hi> Bills are on the File, or regiſtred in Order in their own Books, which is their juſtification from all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentations.</p>
            <p>Again, they ſufficiently confeſs their ignorance, by calling in <hi>Phyſicians</hi> when their own, or any of their relations healths are concerned, and the ſame all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple acknowledge, when they are in diſtreſs and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And very few underſtanding perſons, and none that are learned and knowing, will truſt them at all. But I ſhall refer the Reader to the forementioned Writer againſt the <hi>Apothecaries, viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Daniel Coxe,</hi> who permitted me to name him here; by whom this and many other things here but briefly touched, are judiciouſly handled, and more largely.</p>
            <p>And as for their ſkill in practice, we daily ſee their groſs errours and omiſſions, being called where they have given Medicines. I ſhall inſtance only in one that hapned at the writing hereof; <hi>viz.</hi> that an <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary</hi> gave ſtrong Purging Pills on the Fit day of a gentle Quartan Ague, which turned it into a violent Fever, to the great hazard of the <hi>Patients</hi> life.</p>
            <p>And at how eaſie rates they practiſe, many of their Bills brought and complained of to our <hi>College,</hi> (in ſome whereof I have ſeen Fees ſet down for Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits) witneſs, wherein upon a ſlight diſeaſe 5<hi>l.</hi> hath been demanded for four days practice. And I have
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:93631:31"/> heard one of them brag, that he commonly had from 20 to
100<hi>l.</hi> beſides preſents, for cure of a Clap (as they call it) which might have been more ſpeedily and ſecurely performed for a manifold leſſer ſum.</p>
            <p>I now come to anſwer ſome ſlight objections; as firſt, that <hi>Phyſicians</hi> are unſkillful in the Art of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Medicines; but ſure thoſe that thus object can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny them that ability which Ladies, and almoſt all ordinary women have; <hi>viz.</hi> of diſtilling of waters of all ſorts, making of Syrups, Conſerves, Preſerves, Powders, Trochiſes, Electuaries (and what not) and as many think, more cleanly and neatly then the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries;</hi> and ſome of them Ointments, and Plaſters, in which two lyes their main ſkill. Some where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to thoſe that underſtand not the way of diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of bodies, and the nature of their mixture may be difficult. Yet this defect they may ſupply by leſſening the number of ingredients, and may perform more with 2, or 3 Simples, then with the larger Compoſitions, as 'tis manifeſt in the uſe of <hi>Galbanum</hi> alone, now uſed and found better then <hi>Emplaſtrum Hyſtericum,</hi> conſiſting of 21 ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients.</p>
            <p>And though as matters now ſtand, <hi>Phyſicians</hi> have not the honour to be counted ſuperiour to <hi>Apothecaries</hi> in their Art, yet every one knows that they alone are the preſcribers and directors of the
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> in what they know, and are able to puzzle them in infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite things that concern their Trade, beſides in Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical preparations, whereof moſt of them are totally ignorant; and ſhould <hi>Phyſicians</hi> withdraw themſelves <pb n="64" facs="tcp:93631:32"/> from their converſation, few pretenders to Phyſic would appear more unſkillful then they, neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to deal with a new Simple, nor a new diſeaſe. And for all their pretences of ſkill in Drugs, 'tis moſt certain that the State makes
<hi>Phyſicians,</hi> not <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> Judges of them; and the Statute of <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. appoints the <hi>College</hi> Cenſors upon Oath, not the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> to judg, and condemn falſe and ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated Medicines.</p>
            <p>A ſecond objection wherewith they flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, is, that the great expence of time in preparing Medicines will keep
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> from this courſe. I anſwer, that the
<hi>Phyſician</hi> needs not ſpend much more then half an hour in a day, one with another, on this work, and may faſter diſpenſe them then the
<hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> to Hoſpitals, who in an afternoon can provide for 100, nay ſometimes 200 ſick men, and carry them to the Hoſpital, and diſpoſe them to each ſingle perſon, which takes up much time, which the
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants need not be put to.</p>
            <p>A third objection is, that this courſe, which before 'twas put in practice they derided, now uſed is railed at, will undo them. I anſwer, that if needs, one or the other muſt be ruined, 'tis more reaſonable that the <hi>Apothecary</hi> ſhould ſuffer then the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> becauſe the one acts but his duty, and for the publick good, but the other are tranſgreſſors of the Law, and act above the Sphere of their ſkill, and do many prejudices to the precious lives, and healths of men; and the rather becauſe 'tis in their own power to prevent this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, by ſtinting the number of their Servants (as 'tis in foreign parts, and in
<hi>England</hi> alſo, in very many if <pb n="65" facs="tcp:93631:32"/> not moſt other Trades. Nay our State allows but a ſet number of Printers) for they acknowledg them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that the exceeding increaſe of their number muſt neceſſarily in a ſhort time bring them all to ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and beggery, and a greater want of ſkill then what they now pretend to. But to anſwer this Objection more fully, I affirm <hi>Apothecaries</hi> have made and do make uſe of ſeveral other ways of ſubſiſtence; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their bare trades (none of which <hi>Phyſicians</hi> can uſe) <hi>viz.</hi> ſome of them in this City as well as in the Country, ſell Grocery-wares, and by both together, gain Eſtates. <hi>Secondly,</hi> They barter in Drugs and other Commodities, ſelling them amongſt themſelves, and to other Tradeſmen. Furthermore, they are now building a Laboratory to make all ſorts of Chymical Medicines, intending to ſupply the whole Nation with them, which muſt neceſſarily undo all the Chymiſts in <hi>London;</hi> and whether in time they will not diſtil Strong-waters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (an eaſie thing for them to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake) and by this means to ruine the Corporation of Diſtillers of Strong-waters, I leave to the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to conceive as they pleaſe. However, this I have heard ſeveral of them ſay, that they reſolve to buy all ſorts of Drugs, and make a Magazine of them, as well as of the greater Compoſitions, at their own Hall; and to ſell them to the Members of their Company, whereby the Trade of the Druggiſt, muſt be much leſſened, if not totally over-thrown. So little regard have they of any other employment but of their own, yet all theſe things they may do without any offence againſt the Laws of the Land. Why then ſhould they, who have ſo many ways of ſubſiſtence, envy, and <pb n="66" facs="tcp:93631:33"/> uſurp unlawfully over the ſingle and lawful way grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Phyſicians</hi> for their livelihood? Or why ſhould they repine, and revile them for advancing their Art, the publick health and profit, and for maintaining their profeſſion by their Pens, and actings againſt themſelves, who are the firſt aggreſſors in this diviſion? Which I profeſs to be the ſole end of theſe preſent papers, and heartily wiſh they may thrive and proſper as long as they conform themſelves to the Laws of Honeſty, Reaſon, and of the Land. Beſides, why may not the Plaiſterer more reaſonably pretend the ſame to the Painter, and many other Trades againſt one another, as the Brick-layer to the Stone-Cutter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that they underſtand the Trade, and that truly too, and that they cannot ſubſiſt without this incroachment? And why ſhould not <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> keep open <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Shops? but that the ſame Law limits thoſe Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as well as prohibits the
<hi>Apothecary</hi> from the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Phyſic. And ſurely the Law and State have no conſideration of thoſe perſons ſubſiſtence, who conform not to them; and why ſhould we have of thoſe, ſubordinate to us, who againſt all good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience take away from us all that is our due, and continually traduce and ſlander us very untruly and deſigningly?</p>
            <p>The laſt objection (and a ſtrange one) is, that in this private way of giving Medicines, <hi>Phyſicians</hi> may poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon their
<hi>Patients.</hi> But this is eaſily retorted upon the
<hi>Apothecaries,</hi> who may themſelves or their Servants do the like, as
'tis known in the poyſoning of Sir <hi>Thomas Overbury;</hi> beſides, ſince it cannot be otherwiſe, but that the <hi>Patient</hi> muſt truſt ſomebody, 'tis better to truſt one <pb n="67" facs="tcp:93631:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> then many; and if one, better him whoſe education will teach him better Morality, (and who hath given his Faith (equivalent to an Oath) twice to the Body of the
<hi>College; viz.</hi> once at his admiſſion as Candidate, and a ſecond time at his admiſſion as Fellow; whereby he promiſeth in theſe words, That he ſhall give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to cauſe miſcarriage, or to deſtroy, or hinder Conception, nor Poyſons (for of ſuch, good Medicines may be made) to an evil purpoſe; nay that he ſhall not even teach them where there is any ſuſpicion of ill uſing of them. Which promiſe is nothing elſe but the Oath propoſed by <hi>Hippoc.</hi> to <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to his Books) then ſuch as want theſe qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and this ſeems to be the reaſon why our Common Law makes it Felony, for any perſon to have any one dy under his hand, unleſs he were a lawful <hi>Phyſician.</hi> More noble and generous was the opinion of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Great, concerning his <hi>Phyſician,</hi> who confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently drank off that Medicine which cured him, though he was before informed by ſome friend that 'twas poyſoned. Neither can Hiſtory it ſelf to my knowledg produce any example, that ever any ſuch fooliſh Villany was acted; Though doubtleſs many lives might have been ſaved if the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> would have complyed with the
<hi>College,</hi> in their propoſed Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for ſelling
<hi>Rats-bane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place I ſhall recite ſome few of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices againſt thoſe <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in particular that make their own Medicines, as to tell the <hi>Patient</hi> that is averſe to Chymical Medicines, that the <hi>Doctor</hi> is Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical, and that becauſe for ſooth he makes his own Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; but to thoſe that affect Chymical, that the <pb n="68" facs="tcp:93631:34"/> 
               <hi>Doctor</hi> is but a Galeniſt, and uſeth only dull and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual remedies, as beſt ſuits to the ſick mans Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. A ſecond is, that if this <hi>Phyſician</hi> be called into a
<hi>Patient,</hi> the <hi>Apothecary</hi> will pretend preſent danger, and in his abſence call in another, or pretend he is abroad when he is not, or elſe that the Caſe requires the counſel of two <hi>Phyſicians;</hi> and what other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices they uſe, I have not well learned.</p>
            <p>Now briefly follow ſome ſmall Scandals they caſt upon the ſaid <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> as firſt that they do it for want of practice; the falſity whereof is known by thoſe few that do act this way already, and ſhortly 'twill be more apparent, when many more of good practice, ſingular parts and honeſty will do the like, and certainly nothing but lazyneſs, ignorance, or want of will to do the utmoſt good they are able for the ſick, can hinder them from ſo doing, except age, infirmity of body, or want of convenience. But ſuppoſe 'tis ſo as they alledg, doubtleſs every man may and ought to uſe all lawful means for his own ſubſiſtence; and do not our adverſaries ſay they are inforced to it, affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that unleſs they give Medicines of themſelves, their acquaintance will go to another
<hi>Apothecary</hi> who will do it, though one of their Company told me, they had power by their Charter to reſtrain practice? Whence (if true) it clearly follows that the whole Company allows it.</p>
            <p>But thoſe <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> that for the reaſons above, cannot nor will not take this courſe, are to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, to do here as the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> did in <hi>France,</hi> for the good of people,
<hi>viz.</hi> to tell their <hi>Patients</hi> the prices of Medicines, and to write their Bills in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, <pb n="69" facs="tcp:93631:34"/> that thereby the
<hi>Patients</hi> may not pay too un rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable for them.</p>
            <p>I now conclude, having performed this ungrateful taſk with as much brevity, mildneſs of Spirit, and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as the buſineſs would permit (and what the prudent Statutes of our <hi>College</hi> require of each of their members, that we ſhall by all honeſt and lawful ways and means proſecute all illiterate <hi>Mountebanks</hi> and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and is no more then the Laws and Charters granted to us allow, and what we twice faithfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe (as much an Oath as we can give)
<hi>viz.</hi> at our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion as Candidate and as Fellow) being obliged to another work of greater difficulty, and concern, long ſince promiſed, having been too long diverted with ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my ſelf for my intended practice, and ſeveral other unavoidable Occaſions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:93631:35"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>REader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>There intervening ſo ſmall a ſpace from the publication of the firſt Edition of theſe Papers to this ſecond; I thought to have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nothing to it, but to have put it out only more correct, as the Title intimates; but ſince ſome Sheets were printed off, I have had the opportunity to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of ſome exceptions taken to them, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but few, I ſhall give the Objectors full ſatisfaction in. Though one anſwer might ſerve for all; <hi>viz.</hi> that an <hi>Apothecary</hi> in the preſence of two <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> ſaid, that he had told me of all theſe Cheats, and indeed they are ſo common, that whoſoever ſhall be converſant with them, may obſerve moſt of theſe to be a great part of their diſcourſe. The Firſt exception againſt <hi>Myrtle-leafs,</hi> that they were not ſhewed the <hi>Cenſors</hi> for <hi>Sena,</hi> a Binder for a Purger; the time I have forgot; the <hi>Cenſors</hi> then were, Sir
<hi>George Ent,</hi> Dr. <hi>Goddard,</hi> Dr. <hi>King,</hi> and my Self; the places, <hi>Tut-hill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> and ſome Shops in <hi>King-ſtreet;</hi> Mr. <hi>Shellberry</hi> being then Maſter of the Company. Secondly, As for
<hi>Muſhrooms</hi> rubbed over with Chalk for <hi>Agaric;</hi> this was found by the <hi>Cenſors</hi> in the <hi>Oid-Baily,</hi> at the Shop of one now dead, and therefore I ſhall ſay no further of it, it being taken notice of by Mr. <hi>Evelyn,</hi> as is intimated before. <hi>p.</hi> 8. A Third is
<hi>Diaſcordium</hi> made of <hi>Honey</hi> and <hi>Bole-Armeniac,</hi> this was diſcovered in a <pb n="71" facs="tcp:93631:35"/> Shop at the end of
<hi>Drury-lane</hi> near <hi>Holborn,</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be ſo by Sir
<hi>George Ent, My Self,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardſon</hi> then Maſter of the Company, and the reſt of the <hi>Cenſors</hi> and <hi>Wardens,</hi> eaſily to be remembred, and was by them taken away to their Hall; a pound whereof I had, and by diſſolution found it to be no otherwiſe; what the
<hi>Apothecaries</hi> did with the large Pot of the remainder I know not. Beſides theſe, I have heard no exception to the whole concerning frauds.</p>
            <p>Now ſince the Cheaters with the Cheatees, moſt inſiſt on the objection of Poyſon; I add to what hath been formerly ſaid, that Poyſons are not neceſſarily to be given in Medicines alone, but may be given in Broaths, Beer, or any other thing taken into the Body, and that without the conſultation or knowledg of any <hi>Phyſician,</hi> and ſurely if any one had a mind to Poyſon his Relations (an Action abominable to the Engliſh Nation) he would rather Act privately himſelf, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many opportunities offered to him, rather then by communicating it to others, make himſelf obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to their diſcovery. But if he ſhould communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to others, 'tis more probable he would commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate it to meaner, and more Mercenary perſons, as <hi>Apothecaries</hi> and Nurſes, at a ſmaller rate and with more ſecurity, then reveal ſuch ſecrets to
<hi>Phyſicians,</hi> Men of Honour, and Honeſty. Furthermore, if any mans life be ſuſpected to be taken away with Poyſon, and by opening the body it ſhould appear ſo (and without which it cannot well appear) the
<hi>Phyſician</hi> is doubtleſs as lyable to the Law as any other perſon whatſoever. So that the <hi>Patient</hi> hath as much moral
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:93631:36"/> ſecurity from this miſchief, as poſſibly can be had, or wiſhed in humane affairs. Nay ſuppoſe the <hi>Phyſician</hi> might be ſo corrupted (as to take away his <hi>Patients</hi> life) he might effect it without the leaſt ſuſpition; either by neglecting, or omitting what was neceſſary, or by giving him unproper Medicines, for which he could be accuſed of ignorance or errour only; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if he had a mind to poyſon, he as well as others, aſſiſtants of Viſitors, might do it ſecurely enough, by conveying into a ſingular Cordial, or any Medicine made by the Shops, and often taken by the <hi>Patient</hi> before with good ſucceſs, a mortal doſe without any knowledg or ſurmiſe of any ſuch horrid practice. Add hereunto what an able <hi>Chirurgeon</hi> ſuggeſted, that <hi>Apothecaries</hi> taking upon them the wrapping up, and Embalming of Bodies (whereby they gain more money then by ſeveral years practice upon them; for their embalming amounts to very great ſums) may upon better reaſon be ſuſpected of poyſoning then any other perſons whatſoever converſant among the ſick; ſince both a particular intereſt and convenience of concealing may induce them to it. Laſtly, did this Objection carry any weight in it, then neither <hi>Phyſicians, Chirurgeons, Apothecaries, Nurſes,</hi> nor Friends, might adminiſter to the ſick; becauſe all theſe, as well as <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> may clandeſtinely poyſon their Relations. And therefore that an Objection ſhould be raiſed by ſuch perſons that have more op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities and advantage (in a thing never proved to be done, becauſe 'tis poſſible only) to hinder ſo manifeſt and publick a profit as hath been proved; appears to be very weak and abſurd.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:93631:36"/>And having done with the Objections made to others, and to my ſelf alſo by ſome of the Company, with whom I have converſed, who huff'd exceedingly at my firſt diſcourſe with them, but departed (ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly at leaſt) well ſatisfied, I am ſure fully and without reply anſwered, and with addition of many other Cheats beſides, which I ſhall not here mention for the reaſons above ſpecified: I ſhall here tranſcribe one gratulatory Letter amongſt many ſent me by a Divine well known in Phyſic, being very compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of moſt I have ſaid, to the end the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities and all learned men may ſee what is like to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of one of the three of their noble profeſſions: The words of the Letter are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">"Your deſign all ingenious perſons approve highly, to whom I have communicated it. 'Tis frequent with a Maſter
<hi>Apothecary</hi> that hath ſerved but 2, or 3 years, nay ſome ſcarce one, to take Apprentices for as little, or leſs time, with a little more money then ordinarily; and preſently they aſſume the Title of
<hi>Doctors,</hi> though they underſtand no more then only to write to a whole-ſale <hi>Apothecary</hi> in your City. And truly their couzenages here in the Country do exceed thoſe in the City. For I have known 2<hi>s.</hi>
6<hi>d.</hi> taken for a little Plaſter of <hi>Galba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> and it is uſual to make one pectoral Syrup ſerve for all; as having occaſion to enquire for Syrup of Jujubs, one of them ingenuouſly confeſſed (not knowing what Jujubs were) that he uſed one pecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Syrup for all, a little varying the colour ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and this a peculiar receipt of his own, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing differing from any in the Diſpenſatory."</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:93631:37"/>As for their oppoſition alſo in the Country, take this one Example. An eminent <hi>Phyſician</hi> of
<hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Frauds,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> betook himſelf to make his own Medicines, taking for his Servant one that was not a Freeman of the ſaid City. Who in his Maſters abſence, and contrary to his command, ſold to an <hi>Apothecary</hi> a Medicine not to be had, or at leaſt pretended not to be had in the Town, for a moſt urgent and neceſſary uſe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> conſpiring together, exhibited a complaint to the Mayor and Court of Aldermen, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring of them, that the ſaid <hi>Phyſician</hi> (who was a Freeman, and had lately born the Office of Mayor) might be diſ-franchiſed. Which being not granted them, they ſet the whole City into ſuch diſorder, that they refuſed to attend the Mayor on a Solemn day (as their Cuſtom is, and are bound to do) with their Flags from their Town-Hall to the Church, which the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Magiſtrates for the preſent qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This relation I had from the then Mayor my Kinſman, in the preſence of a <hi>London Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next as to the Lyes and Scandals of my ſelf, I ſhall take notice only of thoſe that concern practice (the reſt being but generally falſe and non-ſenſical revilings.) One is, that they moſt untruly entitle me to have been <hi>Phyſician</hi> to the Lady <hi>Anderſon,</hi> and many others which I never ſaw or heard of; and that I ſoon diſpatched them. Another wherewith they make great noiſe, is, of one Mr.
<hi>Staples</hi> in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent-Garden,</hi> whom they ſay alſo I diſpatched in few days. The true relation whereof was this. An able
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:93631:37"/> 
               <hi>Phyſician</hi> of the <hi>College</hi> had him in hand for the <hi>Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,</hi> about two Months before I was called, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we conſulted and writ a note to the <hi>Apothecary;</hi> a week after the conſultation I was ſent for, and deſired to take care of him alone; he was then, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Jaundice,</hi> troubled with continual Torments in his Bowels, which were as hard as a Board (as they ſay) his Stomach gone, his nights reſtleſs, a vehement Cough joyned with a Hectick Fever, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving long before had an ill Habit of Body. In this Caſe I found him, and in a Months time or thereabouts, I cured his <hi>Jaundice,</hi> relieved his Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, removed the hardneſs of his Bowels, miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated his Cough, but the Hectick Fever continuing he declined; at length another
<hi>Phyſician</hi> was called in, who can witneſs the truth of what was done, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole we had good reaſon to think his Liver to be Apoſtemated. After which conſultation he had no more of me, telling me he would rely on Kitchin Phyſic, and after that I never ſaw him. Now this being the only relation I have heard in this kind, I have been the larger to recite it, that thereby the Reader may take an eſtimate of their dealing with me in the like reports. The like or worſe, ſome of them have ſaid of other <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> which perhaps hereafter ſhall be more fully related with all the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances.</p>
            <p>As for their malicious anger, and diſadvantageous to themſelves, take this one example; I having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed a Plaſter for the Head, an <hi>Apothecary</hi> would not make it, becauſe preſcribed by me; and I have been informed that many of them agreed they would
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:93631:38"/> make nothing for ſuch <hi>Phyſicians</hi> as made their own Medicines; a poor and pitiful revenge, to their own loſs and diſcredit.</p>
            <p>Another Scandal is, the fewneſs of my Medicines. 'Tis true my Cloſet is not open to every bodies Eye, nor have I ſo many and large Pots and Glaſſes, or fill'd with as good as nothing, or the ſame Medicine, in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral with different Titles, neither are any of mine guilded to make a ſhew with; yet I dare offer to view with the beſt of their Shops, for number of good and really uſeful Medicines fit to anſwer preſently any
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> intentions, for internal remedies. And this will be atteſted by ſome of my learned <hi>Collegues,</hi> who have ſeen and peruſed them. Whereas the Shops contain only ſome general Medicines, whereof few ſingle <hi>Phyſicians</hi> make uſe of one quarter in their practice, and upon moſt particular caſes are compell'd to preſcribe what is not readily diſpenſed in the Shops. Others infinuate my ſeldom change of Medicines. To which I anſwer, that where all circumſtances are the ſame, and a good ſucceſs follows; I neither do, nor will much vary, the eaſieſt thing in the World to be done, both to colour and taſt. For ſuch changes (ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be uſed in Shop-practice) without manifeſt reaſon, clog a Patients Purſe and Stomach, may not ſuit with the Patients Diſeaſe nor Conſtitution. And doubtleſs every
<hi>Phyſician</hi> writes at firſt what he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives moſt fit, and proper in the Caſe propoſed; and if this agrees fully to his expectation, runs ſome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard in the alteration, which he is neceſſitated to do in the Shop-way, for many reaſons before-mentioned. Beſides, who ſcruples to take the Medicinal Waters of <pb n="77" facs="tcp:93631:38"/> 
               <hi>Epſom, Barnet,</hi> and
<hi>Tunbridge,</hi> many weeks together? or who refuſeth a conſtant unalter'd Diet-Drink for ſome Months, or Years together? And do not
<hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> in all Diſeaſes of the Lungs, fly to their pectoral decoction for all perſons, and for the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at all times, unleſs perhaps with the addition of a little <hi>China</hi> to it?</p>
            <p>Some Patients of the middle rank have by theſe and ſuch like Artifices been drawn from me, but have ſoon returned, being undeceived by the fulſomneſs, charge, and the non-ſucceſs of the Shops.</p>
            <p>Now theſe things I have here publiſhed to this end alone, that both <hi>Phyſician</hi> and <hi>Patient</hi> may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of them; the former to neglect and ſlight ſuch poor Calumnies, and the other to avoid the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies thence ariſing.</p>
            <p>The care I had not to injure any particular perſon, by naming him in my firſt Edition, or this (although I had ſo many witneſſes of credit, as appears by the Poſtſcript, to juſtifie any thing they can object againſt) makes me hope they will leave off their perſonal ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities, or redreſs their Crimes, their Vanity of threatning me with
20000<hi>l.</hi> Actions, and affrighting my publiſhing this, together with my further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, by their intended aſſaults and batteries; which make them appear ſo ridiculous, that I ſmile at the firſt, and pardon the laſt, wiſhing them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſeriouſly how the expectation ſome have of what they can ſay for themſelves, together with the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity that obliges them to it (if poſſible) were enough one would think, beſides their many large brags of a ſpeedy and full anſwer (which they have a <pb n="78" facs="tcp:93631:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> long time buzzed about the Town as a preſent remedy in this exigence) this I ſay were enough to make any man conclude them guilty, but 'tis hoped this Edition will either work in them an amendment, or bury their confident preſumptions, leaving no man a belief of their innocency. If their promiſed anſwer be any thing elſe but Libelling, or a Ballad without rhime or reaſon, ſtuft with falſities and revilings, ſuch as was only given to Dr. <hi>Coxe</hi>'s Book; I ſhall return it a ſpeedy and full anſwer, and with an addition of far greater Frauds and Abuſes, if they therein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Feb. 20 69/70.</date> Hatton-Garden.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>PAg. 35. l. 6. read <hi>Physician,</hi> pag. 67. l. 12. read then to truſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93631:40"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93631:40"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93631:41"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93631:42"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
